<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-authority-registry-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Human Authority Registry">A Human Authority Registry for Agent-Action Authorization</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authority-registry-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="2"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>authority</keyword>
    <keyword>registry</keyword>
    <keyword>separation of duties</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Workload-identity work answers "which machine acted" and
      token work answers "what was requested." Neither answers a
      question a high-consequence authorization depends on: <em>is the
      human whose signature backs this action actually entitled to
      approve this class of action, for this organization, right now, with
      this key — and are they barred from approving their own request?</em></t>
      <t>This document defines the Human Authority Registry: the
      authoritative record a verifier or enforcement point consults to
      decide whether an authorization receipt
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> was produced
      by an in-scope, currently authorized approver. It specifies the
      registry entry (approver identity, organization, permitted action
      classes, maximum assurance class, validity window, signing keys,
      revocation status, self-approval and quorum constraints), the
      verification rule binding a receipt to an active entry, and how the
      relevant registry state is distributed for offline checking. It is
      complementary to workload-identity and delegation work, not a
      replacement for either.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>An authorization receipt proves that some keyholder signed an
      exact action. Whether that keyholder was <em>allowed</em> to
      authorize that action is a separate question, and it is the
      question that turns a signature into an accountable authorization.
      Today that entitlement lives in scattered, operator-internal
      places: an IAM group, a spreadsheet of approvers, an application's
      own database. None of it is portable, and none of it lets a third
      party — an auditor, a counterparty, a regulator — confirm offline
      that the human who signed was authorized to.</t>
      <t>This document defines a registry for exactly that: the record of
      which humans may approve which action classes, for which
      organization, during which window, with which keys, subject to
      revocation and separation-of-duties constraints. It is deliberately
      about <em>human authority for actions</em>, distinct from workload
      identity (which principal is running) and from delegation of
      machine scope. It composes with the authorization-receipt and
      enforcement-point profiles: the receipt carries the signature, the
      registry says whether the signer was entitled, and the enforcement
      point consults both.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Approver</dt>
        <dd>A named, accountable human entitled to authorize actions.</dd>
        <dt>Registry</dt>
        <dd>The authoritative collection of authority entries defined
        here.</dd>
        <dt>Entry</dt>
        <dd>One approver's authority record (<xref target="entry"/>).</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="entry">
      <name>Authority Entry</name>
      <t>An authority entry is a record with at least the following
      fields:</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>approver_id (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>A stable identifier for the accountable human.</dd>
        <dt>org (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>The organization on whose behalf the approver may authorize.</dd>
        <dt>action_classes (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>The set of action types or classes the approver may
        authorize. An authorization for an action outside this set MUST
        NOT be accepted.</dd>
        <dt>max_assurance_class (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>The highest assurance class the approver may assert (see the
        assurance-class taxonomy). An entry does not raise a receipt's
        proven class; it bounds it.</dd>
        <dt>keys (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>The public key(s) the approver signs with. A receipt whose
        signing key is not among these MUST NOT be attributed to this
        approver.</dd>
        <dt>valid_from / valid_until (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>The window during which the entry is effective. An
        authorization timestamped outside the window MUST be refused.</dd>
        <dt>revoked (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>Revocation status and effective time. A key or entry revoked
        as of time T invalidates authorizations produced after T.</dd>
        <dt>self_approval_forbidden (REQUIRED)</dt>
        <dd>Whether this approver may authorize an action they also
        initiated. When true (the RECOMMENDED default for high-risk
        actions), an authorization whose initiator equals the approver
        MUST be refused.</dd>
        <dt>quorum_eligible (OPTIONAL)</dt>
        <dd>Whether this approver may count toward a Class Q quorum, and
        any group constraints on distinctness.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verify">
      <name>Verification Rule</name>
      <t>An authorization receipt is <em>authority-backed</em> for an
      action if and only if, at the authorization time:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>the receipt's signing key resolves to a registry entry;</li>
        <li>the entry is within its validity window and not revoked as of
        the authorization time;</li>
        <li>the action's class is within the entry's
        <tt>action_classes</tt>;</li>
        <li>the receipt's proven assurance class does not exceed the
        entry's <tt>max_assurance_class</tt>;</li>
        <li>if <tt>self_approval_forbidden</tt> is true, the approver is
        not the initiator of the action; and</li>
        <li>for a Class Q authorization, each contributing approver
        satisfies (1)–(5) and the approvers are distinct and
        quorum-eligible.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>If any condition fails, the receipt MUST NOT be treated as
      authority-backed, and a verifier that cannot resolve the entry MUST
      fail closed.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="offline">
      <name>Offline Verification</name>
      <t>Auditors, counterparties, and edge deployments frequently verify
      without live access to the registry. A registry operator SHOULD
      publish signed, timestamped registry snapshots (or per-entry signed
      attestations) so a relying party can perform the
      <xref target="verify"/> checks offline against a snapshot whose
      freshness it can bound. A snapshot older than a relying party's
      freshness policy MUST be treated as unable to establish authority,
      not as granting it.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Relationship to Other Work</name>
      <t>This registry is about human approval authority for actions. It
      is orthogonal to workload identity (WIMSE), which establishes which
      software principal is running, and complementary to delegation and
      authorization-evidence-chain work
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain"/>, which
      binds a delegation from a human authority root down to an acting
      agent. The registry is the source of truth for the human-authority
      root those chains terminate in, and the entitlement an enforcement
      point checks a receipt against.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>The registry is a trust root; protect it accordingly.</strong>
      Whoever can write an entry can authorize approvers. Registry writes
      MUST be strongly controlled and auditable, and snapshots MUST be
      signed so relying parties detect tampering.</t>
      <t><strong>Revocation propagation.</strong> The security of
      revocation depends on relying parties consulting sufficiently fresh
      state. Offline verifiers MUST enforce a freshness bound on
      snapshots; a stale snapshot cannot be used to accept an
      authorization from a since-revoked key.</t>
      <t><strong>Separation of duties.</strong> The
      <tt>self_approval_forbidden</tt> and quorum-distinctness rules are
      the defense against a single compromised or coerced insider
      authorizing their own high-risk action; they MUST be enforced at
      verification, not merely recorded.</t>
      <t><strong>Bounding, not granting.</strong> An entry bounds what an
      approver may assert; it never raises a receipt's proven assurance
      class. Proven assurance still comes from the receipt's own evidence.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner"/>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author fullname="B. Leiba" initials="B." surname="Leiba"/>
          <date year="2017" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP)</title>
          <author fullname="I. Schrock" initials="I." surname="Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-05"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Evidence Chain (EP)</title>
          <author fullname="I. Schrock" initials="I." surname="Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="June"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-00"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
