<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-reliance-agreement-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Reliance Agreement">Reliance Agreements: Signed Liability Terms Conditioned on Authorization-Evidence Sufficiency</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-reliance-agreement-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="12"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>reliance</keyword>
    <keyword>liability</keyword>
    <keyword>indemnity</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The authorization-evidence stack for high-risk agent actions
      produces verdicts: signed artifacts are presented, replayed
      against a relying party's pinned evidence policy, and found
      admissible or not. The commercial layer above the verdict, who
      bears the loss when a relying party acts on evidence that
      satisfied the policy, exists today only in prose. Insurers
      underwrite AI-agent operations against control standards written
      in natural language; no interoperable signed object expresses
      "if the presented evidence satisfies reliance profile P, these
      liability terms apply between us." This document defines the
      Reliance Agreement (EP-RELIANCE-AGREEMENT-v1): a machine-readable
      object, signed by every party its own required-signer list names,
      in which an issuer, a relying party, and optionally an
      underwriter condition a liability shift or an indemnity (with cap
      amounts as decimal strings) on authorization-evidence sufficiency,
      referencing the evidence condition by digest of a reliance
      profile rather than restating policy. It also defines the
      Reliance Event (EP-RELIANCE-EVENT-v1), the per-action claim
      instrument binding one action's evidence verdict to the
      agreement. Verifying these objects proves who agreed to what
      terms over which evidence conditions, and that a specific
      reliance occurred inside the agreement's scope and window. The
      object is the interoperable expression of an agreement, designed
      to be incorporated by reference into a prose master agreement; it
      is not a substitute for contract law, and enforceability is
      jurisdiction-dependent and out of scope.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Signed-evidence formats for agent actions answer "did a named
      human authorize this exact action, and does the packet satisfy my
      policy?" Authorization receipts
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> carry the
      approval; evidence graphs and policy replay
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/> turn
      heterogeneous artifacts into a closed verdict; assurance classes
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-assurance-classes"/> grade how
      strong the human proof is. What none of these carries is the
      commercial consequence of the verdict: when a bank wires funds, a
      platform executes an irreversible action, or a processor
      dispenses against evidence that satisfied the pinned policy, who
      bears the loss if the underlying authorization was nonetheless
      wrong?</t>
      <t>The market has already priced this question. Insurance
      products for AI-agent operations exist today: certification-plus-
      coverage programs such as AIUC-1 with Lloyd's market capacity,
      Munich Re's aiSure performance guarantees, and Armilla's
      AI-liability coverage underwritten with Chaucer. These are
      evidence that the economics exist ahead of the interoperable
      object: each conditions coverage on controls and evidence
      described in prose policy wordings and audit standards. A relying
      party cannot mechanically discover, verify, or present the terms
      it is relying under; an underwriter cannot mechanically bind
      coverage to the exact evidence condition its actuaries priced;
      and a dispute forum receives narrative, not signed structure.</t>
      <t>This document defines the missing object. A Reliance Agreement
      is a signed, portable, offline-verifiable statement by named
      parties: if the evidence presented for an action in this scope
      satisfies the reliance profile identified here by digest, then
      these liability terms (a liability shift or an indemnity, with
      caps, currency, and deductible) apply between us, in this window.
      A Reliance Event is the per-action record that a specific relying
      party relied, for a specific action digest, on a specific
      evidence verdict, under a specific agreement. Together they make
      the commitment and the reliance non-repudiable and portable. They
      deliberately do not make either enforceable; see
      <xref target="scope-honest"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
        all capitals, as shown here.</t>
        <t>Issuer: the party whose evidence infrastructure produces the
        authorization evidence (typically the operator of the receipt
        and verification stack). Relying party: the party that acts on
        the evidence (executes the wire, dispenses, releases).
        Underwriter: an optional third party that carries or reinsures
        the financial exposure. Reliance profile: the relying-party
        evidence policy object (for example EP-RELIANCE-PROFILE-v1)
        that the reliance verdict is computed under, identified in this
        document only by digest. Reliance result: the record of one
        action's evidence verdict under a reliance profile.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="agreement">
      <name>The Reliance Agreement (EP-RELIANCE-AGREEMENT-v1)</name>
      <t>A Reliance Agreement is a JSON object. Its signable payload is
      the object without the signatures member, serialized with JSON
      Canonicalization Scheme (JCS) <xref target="RFC8785"/> and
      prefixed with the domain-separation string
      "EP-RELIANCE-AGREEMENT-v1" followed by a single NUL octet. Every
      signature in the signatures array is an Ed25519
      <xref target="RFC8032"/> signature over those exact bytes.</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "version": "EP-RELIANCE-AGREEMENT-v1",
  "agreement_id": "ra:example-issuer:example-bank:2026-001",
  "parties": {
    "issuer":        { "id": "ep:org:example-issuer",
                       "key_id": "ep:key:issuer-1" },
    "relying_party": { "id": "ep:org:example-bank",
                       "key_id": "ep:key:rp-1" },
    "underwriter":   { "id": "ep:org:example-underwriter",
                       "key_id": "ep:key:uw-1" }
  },
  "required_signers": ["issuer", "relying_party", "underwriter"],
  "scope": {
    "action_families": ["wire_transfer", "ach_credit"],
    "jurisdictions": ["US-NY"],
    "validity": { "not_before": "2026-01-01T00:00:00Z",
                  "not_after":  "2027-01-01T00:00:00Z" }
  },
  "condition": {
    "reliance_profile_digest": "sha256:<64 hex>",
    "min_assurance_class": "V",
    "max_staleness_sec": 300
  },
  "terms": {
    "mode": "indemnity",
    "cap_amount": "1000000.00",
    "currency": "USD",
    "per_action_cap": "250000.00",
    "aggregate_cap": "1000000.00",
    "deductible": "10000.00"
  },
  "recourse_ref": "https://example.com/master-agreement#annex-b",
  "signatures": [
    { "party": "issuer", "algorithm": "Ed25519",
      "key_id": "ep:key:issuer-1", "signature_b64u": "..." },
    { "party": "relying_party", "algorithm": "Ed25519",
      "key_id": "ep:key:rp-1", "signature_b64u": "..." },
    { "party": "underwriter", "algorithm": "Ed25519",
      "key_id": "ep:key:uw-1", "signature_b64u": "..." }
  ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <section anchor="agreement-fields">
        <name>Field Semantics</name>
        <t>version MUST be EP-RELIANCE-AGREEMENT-v1. agreement_id
        identifies the agreement for correlation; verification MUST NOT
        depend on its uniqueness. parties declares the roles from the
        closed set issuer, relying_party, underwriter; issuer and
        relying_party are REQUIRED, underwriter is OPTIONAL, and an
        unknown role name MUST be refused. Each party carries an id and
        a key_id; the key_id names the key a verifier must have pinned
        out of band, and a verifier MUST NOT trust any key material
        carried in the object itself.</t>
        <t>required_signers is the agreement's own effectiveness rule:
        the list of roles whose signatures make the agreement
        effective. It MUST be non-empty, MUST NOT contain duplicates or
        undeclared roles, and MUST include both issuer and
        relying_party (an agreement neither issued nor accepted is not
        an agreement). An agreement missing any required signature, or
        carrying any signature (required or not) that does not verify
        under the pinned key for that party's key_id, is not effective
        and MUST be refused.</t>
        <t>scope.action_families is a non-empty list of the action
        families the terms cover, from the same vocabulary the relying
        party's evidence policy uses. scope.jurisdictions is an
        OPTIONAL list of jurisdiction labels; it is descriptive
        metadata for the prose master agreement, not a mechanism this
        document verifies. scope.validity gives the window
        (not_before, not_after) in which the agreement is effective;
        both are REQUIRED and not_before MUST precede not_after.</t>
        <t>condition.reliance_profile_digest is the heart of the
        object: the sha256 digest of the JCS-canonical reliance profile
        the terms are conditioned on. The agreement references evidence
        policy by digest and never restates it; the profile itself is
        exchanged, pinned, and replayed through the existing evidence
        machinery. condition.min_assurance_class OPTIONALLY names the
        minimum assurance class
        <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-assurance-classes"/> from the
        closed set S, H, V, Q. condition.max_staleness_sec OPTIONALLY
        bounds the acceptable age of the evidence verdict, in
        seconds.</t>
        <t>terms.mode is from the closed set liability_shift (the
        issuer assumes the loss the relying party would otherwise bear)
        and indemnity (the issuer or underwriter reimburses the relying
        party up to the caps); any other value MUST be refused. Every
        monetary amount (cap_amount REQUIRED; per_action_cap,
        aggregate_cap, deductible OPTIONAL) MUST be a decimal string.
        A monetary amount expressed as a JSON number MUST be refused:
        floating-point representation of money is a correctness
        failure, not a style choice, and a verifier that silently
        accepts 0.1 + 0.2 semantics into a liability cap has already
        lost the dispute. terms.currency MUST be a three-letter
        uppercase currency code applying to all amounts in the
        agreement. recourse_ref OPTIONALLY points to the prose master
        agreement or dispute procedure this object is incorporated
        into; see <xref target="scope-honest"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="event">
      <name>The Reliance Event (EP-RELIANCE-EVENT-v1)</name>
      <t>A Reliance Event is the per-action claim instrument: the
      relying party's signed record that, at a stated time, it relied
      on a specific evidence verdict for a specific action under a
      specific agreement. Its signable payload is the object without
      the signature member, JCS-canonicalized and prefixed with
      "EP-RELIANCE-EVENT-v1" followed by a single NUL octet, signed
      Ed25519 by the agreement's relying party.</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "version": "EP-RELIANCE-EVENT-v1",
  "event_id": "rev:example-bank:2026-07-08:0001",
  "agreement_digest": "sha256:<64 hex>",
  "action_digest": "sha256:<64 hex>",
  "reliance_result_digest": "sha256:<64 hex>",
  "relied_at": "2026-07-08T11:59:00Z",
  "signature": { "party": "relying_party", "algorithm": "Ed25519",
                 "signature_b64u": "..." }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>agreement_digest is the sha256 digest of the agreement's
      domain-prefixed canonical payload (signatures excluded).
      action_digest is the digest of the canonical action relied on,
      the same digest the evidence stack binds receipts and verdicts
      to. reliance_result_digest is the sha256 digest of the
      JCS-canonical reliance result record. The result record MUST
      carry the action_digest it attests and the action_family of the
      action, and MAY carry the digest of the profile it was evaluated
      under and the verdict itself. relied_at is the time of reliance
      and MUST fall inside the agreement's validity window.</t>
      <t>The three digests are the point of the object: the event joins
      one action, one evidence verdict, and one set of agreed terms by
      digest, so that no party can later substitute a different
      verdict, a different action, or a different version of the terms
      into the record of what happened.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="verification">
      <name>Verification</name>
      <t>Verification is offline, deterministic, and fail-closed: any
      check that cannot be completed, any unknown vocabulary value, and
      any malformed field yields a refusal with a stated reason, never
      an exception and never a permissive default.</t>
      <t>Agreement verification proceeds in order: (1) structure, with
      all closed vocabularies (party roles, required_signers, terms
      mode, assurance class) and the amounts-as-strings rule enforced;
      (2) canonical form, computing the exact domain-prefixed JCS bytes
      every signature covers; (3) the validity window against
      verification time; (4) signatures: every role in required_signers
      MUST have exactly one signature entry, every signature present
      (required or not) MUST verify under the key pinned for that
      party's key_id, and a missing pin is a refusal, not a skip.</t>
      <t>Event verification proceeds in order: (1) event structure,
      including digest formats and a relied_at that is parseable and
      not in the future of verification time; (2) the referenced
      agreement MUST verify, with the validity window evaluated at
      relied_at, so the question answered is "was the agreement
      effective when reliance occurred", not "is it effective now";
      (3) the event's agreement_digest MUST equal the digest computed
      over the supplied agreement; (4) the event's action_digest MUST
      equal the action digest the supplied reliance result attests, and
      the reliance_result_digest MUST equal the digest computed over
      the supplied result; (5) the result's action family MUST be
      inside the agreement scope, and when the result names the profile
      it was evaluated under, that digest MUST equal the agreement's
      condition.reliance_profile_digest; (6) the event signature MUST
      verify under the pinned key of the agreement's relying party. A
      signature by any other party, however valid, MUST be refused: the
      claim instrument is meaningful only from the party that bore the
      decision.</t>
      <t>Event verification binds; it does not re-judge. Whether the
      verdict inside the reliance result is honest is established by
      replaying the evidence against the profile the agreement pins by
      digest, using the evidence machinery of
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/>; this
      document's verifier proves only that the claimed verdict, the
      claimed action, and the agreed terms are the ones bound
      together.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="scope-honest">
      <name>What This Object Is and Is Not</name>
      <t>This section is normative in spirit even where it uses no
      capitalized keywords, because the most likely failure of this
      object is overclaim by its own users.</t>
      <t>A Reliance Agreement is the machine-readable EXPRESSION of a
      reliance agreement, not a substitute for contract law. It is
      designed to be incorporated by reference into a prose master
      agreement, in the same way an ETSI signature policy
      <xref target="ETSI-TS-119-172-1"/> or an eIDAS trust-service
      practice statement gives a machine-checkable core its legal force
      through the surrounding prose instrument. The recourse_ref field
      exists exactly for that incorporation; a deployment that signs
      the object without a governing prose agreement has produced
      evidence of intent, not a contract, and should know the
      difference.</t>
      <t>Verifying the object proves WHO agreed (the pinned keys of the
      named parties), to WHAT terms (mode, caps, currency, window,
      scope), over WHICH evidence conditions (the profile digest and
      assurance floor). It does not prove that any party will honor the
      terms, that the terms are enforceable in any jurisdiction, that
      the caps are funded, or that a court or arbitrator will read the
      object the way its signers did. Enforceability is
      jurisdiction-dependent and out of scope for this document.</t>
      <t>A satisfied condition is not an automatic payout. The
      agreement conditions liability terms on evidence sufficiency; it
      does not adjudicate causation, loss quantum, exclusions, or fraud
      by the relying party itself. Those live in the prose instrument
      and its forum. What the objects contribute to that forum is
      structure: a non-repudiable record of the terms, the evidence
      condition, the verdict relied on, and the moment of reliance,
      each bound by digest.</t>
      <t>A Reliance Event records reliance; it does not create
      entitlement. An event that verifies proves the relying party
      claimed, under its own signature, to have relied on a specific
      verdict for a specific action while the agreement was effective.
      Whether that reliance was reasonable, whether the verdict was
      honestly computed, and whether the loss claimed flows from the
      action are questions for the evidence replay and the forum, in
      that order.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="related">
      <name>Relationship to Existing Work</name>
      <t>Rules languages. LegalRuleML <xref target="LegalRuleML"/> and
      the Accord Project's template model <xref target="Accord"/> are
      substrates in which the semantics of an agreement like this one
      could be expressed: LegalRuleML as a formal rule interchange for
      legal norms, Accord as executable natural-language contract
      templates. This document deliberately defines the minimal
      interoperable OBJECT, not a rules language: three party roles, a
      digest-referenced evidence condition, a closed two-mode term
      vocabulary, string amounts, and multi-party signatures over
      canonical bytes. A deployment that needs richer clause logic can
      express it in those substrates and still exchange this object as
      the interoperable core both sides verify.</t>
      <t>The four-corner precedent. The closest historical precedent is
      the IdenTrust (Identrus) four-corner model of the early 2000s:
      banks issued identity certificates, relying banks obtained
      structured warranty messaging around reliance on those
      certificates, and liability flowed through operating rules
      written in prose. It demonstrated that structured, bank-grade
      reliance messaging is buildable and commercially wanted; it was
      also proprietary, closed to one federation, and is defunct as a
      scheme. This document is the open-standard version of that
      lesson: the warranty-shaped object survives the federation that
      first needed it only if anyone can implement and verify it.</t>
      <t>Verifiable Credentials. The W3C Verifiable Credentials data
      model <xref target="VC-DATA-MODEL"/> defines a termsOfUse
      property as a generic extension point on credentials and
      presentations. It carries no liability semantics: no party roles,
      no caps, no evidence condition, no effectiveness rule. A VC
      deployment could carry a Reliance Agreement digest inside
      termsOfUse, but the agreement object itself, with its own
      multi-party signatures, is what this document defines and what
      termsOfUse lacks.</t>
      <t>The prose market. AIUC-1 certification with Lloyd's market
      coverage, Munich Re's aiSure, and Armilla's coverage underwritten
      with Chaucer are named here neutrally as the market signal: the
      willingness to price AI-agent liability against control evidence
      already exists. Today each program binds coverage to controls
      through prose wordings and bespoke audits. An interoperable
      agreement object lets any such program state its evidence
      condition as a pinned profile digest and its terms as a signed
      object any relying party and any forum can verify; nothing in
      this document depends on, or is endorsed by, any of those
      programs.</t>
      <t>The EP evidence stack. Authorization receipts
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> supply the
      action-bound human approval; evidence graphs and policy replay
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/> compute the
      admissibility verdict a reliance result records; assurance
      classes <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-assurance-classes"/> supply
      the ordered vocabulary condition.min_assurance_class draws from.
      This document adds no evidence type and no verdict; it adds the
      commercial commitment layer that consumes them.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Dishonor. An agreement object cannot prevent a party from
      dishonoring it. What it changes is the dispute: the commitment,
      the evidence condition, the verdict, and the moment of reliance
      are each signed or digest-bound, so dishonor becomes attributable
      and the record is portable to whatever forum the prose master
      agreement names. The object converts "we never agreed to that"
      from a factual dispute into a cryptographic one.</t>
      <t>Caps are claims, not escrow. cap_amount and its siblings are
      signed statements of intent about financial exposure. Nothing in
      this document funds, reserves, or escrows them, and a verifier
      MUST NOT present a verified agreement as proof of ability to
      pay.</t>
      <t>Key compromise. A compromised signer key forges commitments:
      an attacker holding the issuer key can sign agreements the issuer
      never made, and one holding the relying-party key can fabricate
      reliance events. Deployments MUST treat agreement-signing keys
      with the same lifecycle discipline as receipt-signing keys,
      including revocation statements; a verifier presented with a
      revocation covering a signer key has a refusal reason, not a
      judgment call. Rotation is why parties carry a key_id rather than
      inline key material: the pin set is the verifier's own trust
      decision, made out of band.</t>
      <t>Digest substitution. The three digests in a reliance event are
      only as good as the canonicalization they are computed over. Both
      objects use JCS <xref target="RFC8785"/> with domain-separation
      prefixes, so an agreement digest can never collide with an event
      digest over the same bytes, and a reliance result is bound
      byte-for-byte, not field-by-field. Verifiers MUST recompute every
      digest from supplied objects and MUST NOT accept a digest match
      asserted by any party.</t>
      <t>Scope laundering. The event verifier refuses a result whose
      action family is outside the agreement scope, and refuses a
      result evaluated under a profile other than the one the agreement
      pins when the result names its profile. It cannot detect a result
      that omits its profile digest and was computed under a weaker
      profile; deployments whose results omit the profile digest have
      chosen to establish that binding by replay instead, and should
      document that choice. The fail-closed floor remains: a result
      naming no action family at all is refused, never waved
      through.</t>
      <t>Amounts. Monetary amounts are decimal strings and a JSON
      number is refused outright. This is a security posture, not
      pedantry: silent binary floating-point conversion of a liability
      cap is an integrity failure that surfaces only at claim time,
      which is the worst possible moment to discover it.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>A future revision will register the media types
      application/ep-reliance-agreement+json and
      application/ep-reliance-event+json. This revision requests no
      IANA action.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8032.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
          <front>
            <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-06"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph/">
          <front>
            <title>Action Evidence Graphs and Evidence Policy Replay for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-AEG)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-assurance-classes" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-assurance-classes/">
          <front>
            <title>Assurance Classes for Authorization Receipts</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-assurance-classes-00"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="LegalRuleML" target="https://docs.oasis-open.org/legalruleml/legalruleml-core-spec/v1.0/legalruleml-core-spec-v1.0.html">
          <front>
            <title>LegalRuleML Core Specification Version 1.0</title>
            <author><organization>OASIS</organization></author>
            <date year="2021" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="Accord" target="https://accordproject.org/">
          <front>
            <title>Accord Project: Open Source Tools for Smart Legal Contracts</title>
            <author><organization>Accord Project, a Series of LF Projects, LLC</organization></author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="VC-DATA-MODEL" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/vc-data-model-2.0/">
          <front>
            <title>Verifiable Credentials Data Model v2.0</title>
            <author><organization>W3C</organization></author>
            <date year="2025" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ETSI-TS-119-172-1" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/119100_119199/11917201/">
          <front>
            <title>Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI); Signature Policies; Part 1: Building blocks and table of contents for human readable signature policy documents</title>
            <author><organization>ETSI</organization></author>
            <date year="2015" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ETSI TS" value="119 172-1"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="impl">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>A reference implementation is published Apache-2.0 in the
      EMILIA Protocol repository
      (packages/verify/reliance-agreement.js): a pure, offline,
      fail-closed verifier for both objects (verifyRelianceAgreement,
      verifyRelianceEvent) with no dependency beyond the platform
      crypto library, plus signing helpers. A conformance suite of
      sixteen vectors (conformance/vectors/reliance-agreement.v1.json,
      exercised by tests/reliance-agreement.test.js) covers the happy
      paths for both objects and the refusals specified here: a missing
      required signature, an expired or not-yet-effective window, a cap
      amount tampered after signing, a cap amount expressed as a JSON
      number, an unknown terms mode, an unpinned required-signer key, a
      required signer the agreement never declared, an event bound to a
      different agreement digest, an event signed by a party other than
      the relying party, a result attesting a different action, an
      action family outside the agreement scope, a result altered after
      the event bound it, reliance outside the agreement window, and a
      result evaluated under a different profile than the agreement
      pins.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
