<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-04"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Authorization Evidence Chains">Authorization Evidence Chains: Composing Heterogeneous Agent-Action Evidence (EP-AEC)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-04"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="27"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>composition</keyword>
    <keyword>replay</keyword>
    <keyword>JCS</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Consequential agent actions can produce heterogeneous identity,
      delegation, policy, permit, approval, transparency, capability, and
      execution artifacts. Each artifact can verify under its own
      specification while still referring to a different action, filling a
      different evidentiary role, or failing a relying party's freshness,
      status, or inter-artifact binding requirement. This document defines
      the Authorization Evidence Chain (EP-AEC): a transport-agnostic
      composition object and a fail-closed evaluation algorithm that preserves
      native verification, establishes exact material-action matching, and
      evaluates a relying-party-pinned evidence requirement.</t>
      <t>AEC produces SATISFIED or UNSATISFIED and a replayable evaluation
      record. SATISFIED means only that the presented evidence filled the
      relying party's named evidence requirement at the stated verification
      time. It is not a universal authorization decision, a policy language
      for the protected application, or proof of execution or outcome. The
      executor makes the separate local AUTHORIZED decision and controls
      consumption, invocation, and effect handling. AEC introduces no new
      component receipt type and does not replace any native verifier.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>One consequential action can produce several independently useful
      artifacts: a workload credential, a delegation record, a policy permit,
      a named-human authorization receipt, a quorum, a bounded-capability
      operation record, or a transparency receipt. These artifacts answer
      different questions. A relying party may require several of them for one
      action.</t>
      <t>Native validity is not sufficient for composition. A valid permit for
      action A and a valid approval for action B do not jointly authorize
      either action. Likewise, two valid artifacts can still be inadequate if
      the relying party required a fresher approval, a checked revocation
      status, or a byte-backed relation showing that one artifact explicitly
      references another.</t>
      <t>EP-AEC provides the thin composition layer. It dispatches artifacts
      to their native verifiers, maps only integrity-protected native action
      commitments to the relying party's expected material action, evaluates
      an evidence requirement owned by the relying party, and records the
      exact inputs to that evidence decision. It does not decide whether the
      protected application should act.</t>

      <section anchor="scope">
        <name>Scope and Non-Goals</name>
        <t>This document defines:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>the EP-AEC-v1 composition object;</li>
          <li>the EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 relying-party evidence requirement;</li>
          <li>a verifier-result contract that keeps native verification
          separate from material-action mapping;</li>
          <li>a fail-closed SATISFIED or UNSATISFIED evaluation; and</li>
          <li>the EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1 evaluation record and replay digest.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>This document does not define a universal evidence taxonomy, a
        general authorization policy language, a component receipt format, an
        application allow or deny decision, a signed reliance-result format,
        a transparency service, or an execution state machine. It does not
        require a graph wire format or make presenter-asserted graph edges
        authoritative.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
      NOT", and "MAY" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
      when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Native verifier</dt>
        <dd>A verifier selected by the relying party for one artifact format
        and revision. It checks that format's syntax, signatures, issuer,
        audience, validity, and format-specific semantics under pinned trust
        inputs.</dd>
        <dt>VERIFIED</dt>
        <dd>The native verifier accepted an artifact under the selected native
        profile. This state alone says nothing about whether the artifact
        denotes the expected material action.</dd>
        <dt>MATCH</dt>
        <dd>A VERIFIED artifact's integrity-protected native action commitment
        denotes the relying party's expected material action by direct exact
        digest equality or by an exact, relying-party-pinned CAID mapping
        profile.</dd>
        <dt>SATISFIED</dt>
        <dd>Eligible evidence filled the relying party's evidence requirement
        at the explicit verification time.</dd>
        <dt>AUTHORIZED</dt>
        <dd>A separate local application decision permitting an invocation.
        AEC does not produce this state.</dd>
        <dt>Evidence digest</dt>
        <dd>The string "sha256:" followed by the lowercase hexadecimal
        SHA-256 digest of an artifact's JCS <xref target="RFC8785"/>
        serialization.</dd>
        <dt>Normalized evidence fact</dt>
        <dd>A verifier-produced, bounded record of native validity,
        material-action mapping, time and status checks, and byte-backed
        bindings for one component. It is not supplied by the presenter.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="object">
      <name>The Authorization Evidence Chain Object</name>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@version": "EP-AEC-v1",
  "action": { "...": "Action Object" },
  "action_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
  "action_caid": "caid:1:<action-type>:<suite>:<digest-b64url>",
  "components": [
    {
      "type": "ep-quorum",
      "label": "two-person human authorization",
      "evidence_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
      "evidence": { "...": "native artifact" }
    },
    {
      "type": "policy-permit",
      "evidence": { "...": "native artifact" }
    }
  ],
  "requirement": "ep-quorum AND policy-permit"
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <ul>
        <li><tt>@version</tt> (string, REQUIRED) MUST equal
        <tt>EP-AEC-v1</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>action</tt> (object, REQUIRED) is the closed Action Object to
        which the evaluation is joined.</li>
        <li><tt>action_digest</tt> (string, OPTIONAL) is descriptive. When
        present, it MUST equal the verifier's recomputation over
        <tt>action</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>action_caid</tt> (string, OPTIONAL) is descriptive. It MUST NOT
        establish its own mapping or trust. When the relying party requires a
        CAID, the verifier recomputes or independently obtains the expected
        CAID and compares it as specified in <xref target="matching"/>.</li>
        <li><tt>components</tt> (array, REQUIRED and non-empty) contains
        <tt>type</tt> (string), <tt>evidence</tt> (JSON value suitable for the
        native format), and optional <tt>label</tt> and
        <tt>evidence_digest</tt> strings. A label is display-only. When an
        evidence digest is present, the verifier MUST recompute and compare
        it before native verification.</li>
        <li><tt>requirement</tt> (string, OPTIONAL) is a presenter-supplied
        description. It MUST NOT become the relying party's sufficiency bar
        and MUST NOT produce SATISFIED.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The chain is a bundle, not an authority-bearing graph. Component
      order is preserved for reporting, but order confers no semantics. All
      credited relations between components come from integrity-protected
      native bytes exposed by a trusted native verifier, never from labels,
      ordering, or presenter-supplied edges.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rp-requirement">
      <name>The Relying-Party Evidence Requirement</name>
      <t>Before returning SATISFIED, a verifier MUST receive an
      EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 object from relying-party-controlled
      configuration. The chain document cannot supply or weaken it.</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@version": "EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1",
  "requirement_id": "treasury-wire-evidence@7",
  "purpose": "pre-execution evidence check",
  "expression": "ep-quorum AND policy-permit",
  "freshness_sec": {
    "ep-quorum": 300,
    "policy-permit": 600
  },
  "status_required": ["ep-quorum"],
  "required_bindings": [
    {
      "from_type": "policy-permit",
      "relation": "permits",
      "to_type": "ep-quorum"
    }
  ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <ul>
        <li><tt>@version</tt> MUST equal
        <tt>EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>requirement_id</tt> is a relying-party identifier for the exact
        evidence requirement revision. It carries no authority by itself.</li>
        <li><tt>purpose</tt> is descriptive and MUST NOT alter expression
        evaluation.</li>
        <li><tt>expression</tt> is REQUIRED and follows
        <xref target="expressions"/>.</li>
        <li><tt>freshness_sec</tt> is an OPTIONAL map from component type to a
        non-negative maximum age in seconds.</li>
        <li><tt>status_required</tt> is an OPTIONAL array of component types
        for which a fresh authenticated status result is required.</li>
        <li><tt>required_bindings</tt> is an OPTIONAL array of
        <tt>from_type</tt>, <tt>relation</tt>, and <tt>to_type</tt> triples.
        Each triple requires at least one eligible source component whose
        native verified bytes bind, under that relation, the evidence digest
        of an eligible target component of the named type.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The verifier MUST compute the requirement profile digest over the JCS
      serialization of the complete requirement object. The requirement
      object controls evidence sufficiency only. Application rules about
      amounts, destinations, operator permissions, legal authority, risk
      acceptance, or whether to execute remain in the separate local
      authorization policy.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acceptance-inputs">
      <name>Relying-Party Acceptance Inputs</name>
      <t>Internal agreement among presenter-supplied artifacts cannot satisfy
      a relying party. The verifier MUST receive these values from trusted
      configuration or from the protected boundary that is about to act:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>the EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 object;</li>
        <li>the expected Action Object or its independently computed canonical
        action digest;</li>
        <li>an expected CAID and mapping profiles when cross-format action
        mapping is used;</li>
        <li>an explicit verification time;</li>
        <li>the native verifier revisions, trust anchors, audiences, freshness
        inputs, and status sources selected for each component type; and</li>
        <li>documented resource limits for parsing, nesting, component count,
        expression size, and verifier execution.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>These values MUST NOT be taken from the presented chain or from an
      untrusted caller. If any required input is absent, malformed, ambiguous,
      or outside its configured validity, the result is UNSATISFIED.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="native-contract">
      <name>Native Verification and Normalized Facts</name>
      <t>AEC does not reinterpret a native signature or token. For each
      component, a relying-party-selected native verifier first returns a
      bounded internal result containing:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>native validity and a machine-readable failure reason;</li>
        <li>the integrity-protected native action commitment, if any;</li>
        <li>the protected issuance and expiration instants needed by the
        selected freshness check;</li>
        <li>the protected issuer, audience, and format revision relevant to
        the selected native profile;</li>
        <li>an authenticated status result and status-snapshot digest when
        status checking is required; and</li>
        <li>zero or more relation and target-evidence-digest bindings extracted
        from integrity-protected native fields.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>A component reaches VERIFIED only when its native verifier succeeds.
      AEC MUST NOT accept a presenter's <tt>verified</tt> Boolean, normalized
      fact, mapping result, key, trust anchor, status assertion, or relation as
      a substitute for native verification.</t>
      <t>A deployment in which a protected boundary performs native
      verification before calling the AEC evaluator MAY pass the verifier
      results internally instead of repeating the cryptographic work. Such
      results MUST be integrity-bound inside the same trust boundary to the
      exact evidence digest, native verifier profile digest, trust snapshot,
      and verification time. Serialized results received from the presenter
      are evidence artifacts of their own and require a native verifier; they
      are not trusted internal results.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="matching">
      <name>Material-Action Matching</name>
      <t>Native verification and material-action matching are distinct and
      ordered. Mapping MUST NOT inspect unverified claims as authoritative
      input.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>The boundary computes the expected action digest from the frozen
        action it is actually preparing to perform.</li>
        <li>The native verifier verifies the component and exposes only its
        integrity-protected native action commitment.</li>
        <li>If that commitment uses the same action representation and digest
        algorithm, exact digest equality establishes MATCH.</li>
        <li>Otherwise, a relying-party-pinned Action-Mapping Profile from
        <xref target="CAID"/> projects the verified native payload to the
        expected CAID action type. Only the CAID verdict
        EQUIVALENT_UNDER_PROFILE establishes MATCH.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>NOT_EQUIVALENT, INDETERMINATE, an unknown mapping revision, a lossy
      projection, a presenter-selected profile, or a mismatch between the
      projected CAID and the expected CAID is not MATCH and MUST make that
      component ineligible. CAID carries content identity, not trust or
      authorization semantics.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="expressions">
      <name>Requirement Expressions</name>
      <t>The expression grammar uses ABNF and its core rules as defined by
      <xref target="RFC5234"/>:</t>
      <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
expr     = term *(WS operator WS term)
term     = ident / "(" WS expr WS ")"
operator = "AND" / "OR" / "&&" / "||"
ident    = 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT / "." / ":" / "-" / "_")
WS       = *(SP / HTAB / CR / LF)
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>An identifier matches a component type with at least one eligible
      component. An unknown identifier evaluates to false. Implementations
      MUST use a bounded parser and MUST NOT use a general-purpose evaluator.
      AND and OR have equal binding strength and are evaluated strictly from
      left to right. Parentheses are the only precedence mechanism.</t>
      <t>This expression deliberately answers only which evidence roles are
      present. It has no variables for action parameters, principals,
      entitlements, business risk, or effect state. Those belong to native
      artifact verification, CAID mapping, or local authorization.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verify">
      <name>Verification Algorithm</name>
      <t>Given chain C and the acceptance inputs in
      <xref target="acceptance-inputs"/>, a verifier MUST proceed
      fail-closed:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Strictly parse C as I-JSON <xref target="RFC7493"/> and enforce all
        configured resource limits. Reject duplicate member names,
        non-integer numbers, malformed Unicode, cycles in an in-memory object,
        and unsupported versions.</li>
        <li>Compute the canonical action digest over C.action. Compare it with
        the executor-owned expected action digest. If C.action_digest is
        present, compare it too. Any mismatch yields UNSATISFIED.</li>
        <li>Validate and digest the relying-party requirement. If the only
        available requirement came from C, yield UNSATISFIED.</li>
        <li><t>For each component in array order:</t>
          <ol type="a">
            <li>Compute its evidence digest. If a presented evidence digest
            exists and differs, mark the component ineligible.</li>
            <li>Invoke the selected native verifier or consume a trusted
            internal verifier result as constrained by
            <xref target="native-contract"/>. Exceptions and unknown verifier
            types make the component ineligible.</li>
            <li>Only after native VERIFIED, establish material-action MATCH
            under <xref target="matching"/>. A different or indeterminate
            action makes the component ineligible.</li>
            <li>If the requirement sets a freshness bound for the component
            type, require protected issuance time, verification time within
            the native validity window, and age not exceeding the bound.
            Future-issued, expired, missing, or malformed times make the
            component ineligible.</li>
            <li>If status is required for the component type, require an
            authenticated, sufficiently fresh status snapshot under the
            selected native profile. Revoked, unknown, stale, or
            unauthenticated status makes the component ineligible.</li>
            <li>Record a normalized fact including component index, type,
            evidence digest, native verifier profile digest, native validity,
            mapping verdict, freshness and status results, and only the
            byte-backed bindings returned by the native verifier.</li>
          </ol>
        </li>
        <li>Construct the satisfied type set from eligible components only and
        evaluate the relying-party expression.</li>
        <li>For every required binding, require an eligible source and target
        pair with matching types and a source native fact whose named relation
        binds the target's exact evidence digest. A label, component order,
        equal action digest, or presenter's relation claim does not satisfy a
        required binding.</li>
        <li>Return SATISFIED only if the expression is true, every required
        binding exists, and every mandatory acceptance check succeeded.
        Otherwise return UNSATISFIED.</li>
        <li>Produce the replay record in <xref target="replay"/>. Any
        unexpected error at any step yields UNSATISFIED and a bounded reason;
        it MUST NOT yield a partial success.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>The result MUST carry <tt>satisfied</tt> as a Boolean and SHOULD carry
      bounded per-component reason codes. An implementation may retain a
      legacy <tt>allow</tt> alias, but that alias MUST equal
      <tt>satisfied</tt> and MUST NOT be interpreted as local AUTHORIZED.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="replay">
      <name>Evidence Evaluation Replay</name>
      <t>An evaluator MUST be able to emit an EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1 record. The
      replay record is an evaluation output, not a presenter input:</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@version": "EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1",
  "aec_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
  "expected_action_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
  "expected_caid": "caid:1:<action-type>:<suite>:<digest-b64url>",
  "requirement_profile_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
  "verification_time": "2026-07-27T17:00:00Z",
  "facts": [ { "...": "normalized evidence fact" } ],
  "satisfied": true,
  "reasons": []
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The <tt>aec_digest</tt> is the evidence digest of the complete
      EP-AEC-v1 object. Facts remain in component array order. Object members
      inside each fact use JCS ordering. The replay digest is the evidence
      digest of the complete EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1 record.</t>
      <t>Given the same AEC object, expected action inputs, requirement
      profile, explicit verification time, normalized native facts, and
      algorithm revision, implementations MUST compute the same replay digest
      and SATISFIED result. Native verification can depend on trust snapshots
      or status services; therefore the replay record MUST bind the selected
      verifier-profile and status-snapshot digests needed to identify those
      inputs. A replay record without the underlying evidence and identified
      trust snapshots can identify a decision but cannot independently prove
      that every recorded native fact was true.</t>
      <t>The replay digest is not a signature, authorization, transparency
      receipt, or current-status proof. Another format MAY sign or log it. This
      document intentionally defines no signed reliance-result envelope and no
      legal meaning for a SATISFIED result.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="human-leg">
      <name>Human-Authorization Components</name>
      <t>AEC does not infer that a generic operator signature, credential,
      policy decision, or attested workload represents a named-human approval
      ceremony. A relying party that needs an EMILIA human authorization or
      quorum requires <tt>ep-receipt</tt> or <tt>ep-quorum</tt> explicitly.</t>
      <t>The <tt>ep-receipt</tt> built-in MUST accept only a Trust Receipt under
      a relying-party profile that pins the approver directory, accepted key
      class, WebAuthn RP ID and signed-origin allowlist where required, policy
      hash, log key, maximum evidence age, verification time, and fresh
      registry snapshot as specified by <xref target="EP-RECEIPTS"/>. A bare
      operator envelope is not an <tt>ep-receipt</tt> human leg.</t>
      <t>The <tt>ep-quorum</tt> built-in MUST compare the presented quorum
      policy with the relying-party-pinned policy and enforce the selected
      approver, role, distinctness, origin, ordering, and freshness rules of
      <xref target="EP-QUORUM"/>. A safety-critical profile requiring human
      separation MUST require at least two distinct humans. A valid quorum
      under presenter-selected keys or a weaker presenter-selected policy is
      ineligible.</t>
      <t>Credential validity and human operation remain distinct. A valid
      credential identifies a key holder under its native profile; it does not
      establish that a human operated an agent for this action, reviewed the
      material fields, or held legal authority.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bounded-capability-leg">
      <name>Bounded-Capability Operation Components</name>
      <t>A static bounded-capability receipt authorizes capability issuance
      and MUST NOT be treated as bound to every later exercise merely because
      the proposed action falls within its scope.</t>
      <t>A <tt>bounded-capability-operation</tt> component is eligible only
      when its native verified operation record binds the exact action and the
      native verifier validates the referenced capability, issuance
      authorization, scope result, and operation record. AEC does not query or
      reserve current budget. A capability component MUST NOT satisfy
      <tt>ep-receipt</tt>, <tt>ep-quorum</tt>, or another human role.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="aeb-lifecycle">
      <name>Position in the Effect-Boundary Lifecycle</name>
      <t>AEC occupies one deliberately narrow transition in the effect-boundary
      lifecycle described by <xref target="EP-AEB"/>:</t>
      <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
native VERIFIED
  -> material-action MATCH
  -> AEC SATISFIED
  -> local AUTHORIZED
  -> atomic CONSUMED or RESERVED
  -> INVOKED
  -> EXECUTED, FAILED, or INDETERMINATE
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>AEC can orchestrate native verification and mapping itself or consume
      trusted internal results from the same protected boundary. In both
      arrangements, VERIFIED precedes MATCH, and both precede SATISFIED. AEC
      MUST NOT collapse SATISFIED into AUTHORIZED, consume an authorization,
      invoke an effect, classify an outcome, or reconcile an indeterminate
      effect.</t>
      <t>One-time consumption is stateful and remains at the effect boundary.
      An offline SATISFIED result cannot prove that another executor has not
      already acted. A consequential executor uses shared atomic state keyed
      by an executor-derived action instance and preserves an uncertain
      operation instead of blindly replaying it.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>Presenter-selected sufficiency.</strong> A presenter can
      construct a weak requirement that its own evidence satisfies. The
      EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 object MUST come from relying-party configuration.
      C.requirement is descriptive only.</t>
      <t><strong>Presenter-selected action.</strong> Agreement among components
      proves only internal agreement. The expected action digest and CAID must
      be computed or selected by the protected boundary from the action it is
      actually preparing to perform.</t>
      <t><strong>Cross-binding.</strong> An attacker can splice individually
      valid artifacts for different actions. Native verification before
      mapping and exact MATCH for each eligible component are required. A
      label, shared principal, shared session, or similar-looking parameter is
      not a match.</t>
      <t><strong>Unbacked relations.</strong> A presenter can claim that one
      artifact permits, delegates to, records, or supersedes another. AEC
      credits a relation only when the trusted native verifier extracts the
      target evidence digest and relation from integrity-protected native
      bytes. An unbacked relation never satisfies a required binding.</t>
      <t><strong>Verifier and key-role confusion.</strong> Native verifiers,
      revisions, trust anchors, mapping profiles, and human directories are
      relying-party pins. They MUST NOT be accepted in the same transaction as
      presenter-controlled evidence. A key trusted for one component role
      does not automatically satisfy another role.</t>
      <t><strong>Freshness and status.</strong> Message freshness, artifact
      age, credential validity, credential revocation, authority revocation,
      and policy revision are separate checks. A current credential does not
      make old per-action evidence fresh. A replay record captures the checked
      instant and snapshots; it does not establish current status later.</t>
      <t><strong>Replay overclaiming.</strong> Deterministic replay shows that
      the same normalized inputs produce the same evidence result. It is not a
      refinement proof, a guarantee that a native verifier was correctly
      implemented, or proof that the recorded external status snapshot was
      honest.</t>
      <t><strong>Resource exhaustion.</strong> Implementations MUST bound JSON
      depth, node count, component count, string bytes, expression tokens and
      depth, binding count, native verifier work, and diagnostic output. Any
      bound exceeded is UNSATISFIED.</t>
      <t><strong>Host-language and transport boundaries.</strong> Strict JSON
      parsing must reject duplicate member names before ordinary object
      construction can hide them. AEC inherits the confidentiality and
      integrity properties of its transport. The evidence and frozen action
      passed to later stages must not be mutable after evaluation.</t>
      <t><strong>Signature overclaiming.</strong> A valid signature establishes
      only the signer and statement semantics of the selected native profile.
      It does not inherently prove a natural person's identity, human
      operation, comprehension, legal authority, safety, execution, or
      outcome.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>An AEC bundle can reveal identities, organizational roles,
      destinations, resources, policy choices, and timing. Presenters and
      relying parties SHOULD disclose and retain only evidence needed by the
      selected requirement. A plain digest of low-entropy personal data is not
      anonymization.</t>
      <t>The replay record SHOULD contain normalized facts and content digests,
      not unnecessary raw evidence. Even those facts can reveal relationships
      and decision timing. Access, retention, and correlation controls remain
      deployment responsibilities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relationship">
      <name>Relationship to Other Work</name>
      <t>CAID <xref target="CAID"/> owns typed material-action identity and
      exact, relying-party-pinned cross-format mapping. AEC uses CAID only
      after native verification and does not add trust semantics to a CAID.</t>
      <t>Authorization Receipts <xref target="EP-RECEIPTS"/> and Quorum
      <xref target="EP-QUORUM"/> define two native human-authorization
      components. AEC composes them without generalizing all evidence into
      those formats.</t>
      <t>The earlier Action Evidence Graph draft <xref target="EP-AEG"/>
      described content-addressed graph references, relying-party evidence
      policy replay, a five-verdict classification, policy packs, and a signed
      reliance result. This revision incorporates the useful composition
      substance into AEC: relying-party-owned evidence requirements,
      content-digested components, byte-backed relations, normalized facts,
      and a replay digest. It intentionally does not adopt the EP-AEG-v1 graph
      envelope, five-verdict taxonomy, policy packs, or signed reliance-result
      format.</t>
      <t>If draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-04 is published, it
      is intended to supersede draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00 for
      this evidence-composition and replay scope. Until publication, the
      posted AEC-03 and AEG-00 remain their respective public snapshots; a
      local staged source does not replace an Internet-Draft.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. It creates no universal component,
      relation, verifier, action-mapping, requirement, reason-code, or policy
      registry.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="changes-04">
      <name>Changes in -04</name>
      <ul>
        <li>Defined EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 so expression, freshness, status,
        and required inter-artifact bindings are pinned by the relying party.</li>
        <li>Defined normalized native facts and EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1 without
        changing the EP-AEC-v1 component envelope or creating a signed
        reliance-result format.</li>
        <li>Made native VERIFIED, CAID material-action MATCH, AEC SATISFIED,
        local AUTHORIZED, and effect outcomes distinct ordered states.</li>
        <li>Required inter-artifact bindings to come from integrity-protected
        native bytes rather than presenter-asserted graph edges.</li>
        <li>Integrated the useful evidence-policy replay substance of AEG-00
        while declining its separate graph envelope, policy packs, and
        five-verdict taxonomy.</li>
        <li>Clarified that AEG-00 is superseded for this scope only if -04 is
        published.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="impl">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>The existing reference verifier implements the EP-AEC-v1 envelope,
      native-verifier dispatch, exact action-digest binding, bounded Boolean
      requirement evaluation, relying-party requirement precedence, built-in
      human legs, and SATISFIED or UNSATISFIED. Same-team TypeScript, Python,
      and Go implementations consume shared vectors; this is cross-language
      consistency testing, not independent implementation.</t>
      <t>The repository also contains an experimental implementation and tests
      for content-digested evidence nodes, required byte-backed relations,
      freshness evaluation, deterministic replay digests, and signed reliance
      results from the earlier AEG design. As of this revision date, the
      combined EP-AEC-REQUIREMENT-v1 and EP-AEC-REPLAY-v1 contract in this
      document is not yet covered by the three-language AEC vector suite.
      Therefore the repository MUST NOT be described as a complete conforming
      implementation of -04 until those combined vectors and implementations
      exist.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      <reference anchor="CAID" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier/">
        <front>
          <title>The Canonical Action Identifier (CAID)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-RECEIPTS" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-08"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-QUORUM" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-quorum/">
        <front>
          <title>Multi-Party Quorum Authorization for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-QUORUM)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-quorum-03"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="EP-AEG" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph/">
        <front>
          <title>Action Evidence Graphs and Evidence Policy Replay for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-AEG)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-AEB">
        <front>
          <title>Action Evidence Boundary: Verification and Consequence Control at the Effecting System</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-action-evidence-boundary-00"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Review of adjacent work sharpened the separation among native
      validity, cross-format action mapping, evidence satisfaction, local
      authorization, credential status, human operation, and effect truth.
      Acknowledgment does not imply endorsement.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
