<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-model-to-matter-00"
     category="exp" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Model-to-Matter">Model-to-Matter: Authorization Evidence for Model-Directed Physical Execution</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-model-to-matter-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal><country>US</country></postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="14"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>physical execution</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>human oversight</keyword>
    <keyword>single-use clearance</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Advanced models and agents can propose experimental workflows and
      invoke systems that produce physical effects. Before acting, a physical
      executor may need evidence from several independent authorities: model
      provenance, a safety assessment, institutional authority, a domain
      review, an external screening service, and an accountable human. Those
      artifacts are commonly evaluated separately and may not bind the same
      action. This document defines Model-to-Matter, an experimental
      executor-side applicability profile for composing those artifacts over
      one canonical, digest-only action. It specifies an executor-owned
      acceptance profile, normalized signed evidence adapters, a registered
      challenge, closed clearance and refusal verdicts, atomic single-use
      clearance consumption, and an optional executor-signed effect statement. The
      profile does not perform domain screening, determine scientific safety,
      authorize an institution, or establish physical truth. It standardizes
      the point at which an executor refuses to act unless the authorities it
      independently trusts agree about the same action.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
      <t>A digital proposal can become a physical effect when a model or agent
      can call a cloud laboratory, instrument gateway, robot, manufacturing
      system, or other executor. Existing controls answer important but
      separate questions: which model and harness produced the proposal,
      whether an assessment ran, whether the principal had institutional
      authority, whether a domain reviewer approved the workflow, whether an
      external screening service returned an acceptable result, and whether a
      responsible human approved execution.</t>
      <t>None of those facts alone answers the executor's question: do all
      authorities required by this executor agree about this exact model,
      harness, protocol commitment, material commitment, purpose, facility,
      destination, and one permitted clearance? A presenter can otherwise
      splice valid artifacts for different actions or choose a weaker
      sufficiency rule.</t>
      <t>Model-to-Matter defines the relying-party side of that boundary. The
      executor constructs the Action Object, pins its own profile and issuer
      keys, challenges for the required evidence, and refuses every result
      except a closed <tt>clear_to_execute</tt> verdict. The challenge and the
      action are consumed in durable shared state before the corresponding
      execution can be credited.</t>

      <section anchor="scope"><name>Scope and Non-Goals</name>
        <t>This document specifies evidence composition and execution custody.
        It does not define a domain's safety criteria, inspect sensitive
        scientific content, replace an institutional review process, certify a
        model or facility, or decide whether an experiment should be approved.
        Each substantive judgment remains with the authority that signs the
        corresponding evidence artifact.</t>
        <t>This document also does not prove that a physical effect occurred or
        that sensors reported it accurately. An effect statement proves only
        what a pinned executor signed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions"><name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
      and "MAY" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
      they appear in all capitals.</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Executor</dt>
        <dd>The system that controls the physical or external effect and
        evaluates Model-to-Matter evidence before acting.</dd>
        <dt>Action Object</dt>
        <dd>The executor-computed, canonical representation of one requested
        physical action.</dd>
        <dt>Evidence issuer</dt>
        <dd>An independent authority that signs one normalized evidence
        artifact. Signature validity does not itself make the issuer accepted.</dd>
        <dt>Relying-party profile</dt>
        <dd>The executor-owned acceptance policy, including evidence types,
        issuer keys, freshness, revocation, action types, and human-assurance
        floor.</dd>
        <dt>Clearance</dt>
        <dd>A closed executor verdict. Only <tt>clear_to_execute</tt> permits the
        guarded execution path.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="architecture"><name>Architecture</name>
      <t>The Model-to-Matter lifecycle has the following participants:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>The executor constructs an Action Object from the operation it is
        actually prepared to perform.</li>
        <li>The executor selects a relying-party profile and registers a
        short-lived challenge binding the action digest and profile digest.</li>
        <li>Independent issuers produce typed evidence artifacts bound to that
        action digest.</li>
        <li>The presenter submits an evidence graph in response to the
        challenge.</li>
        <li>The executor atomically consumes the challenge, verifies every
        evidence leg under its pinned profile, and emits one closed verdict.</li>
        <li>Before returning <tt>clear_to_execute</tt>, the executor atomically
        consumes the action digest so separately issued challenges cannot
        authorize the same action twice.</li>
        <li>After attempting the effect, the executor may issue a signed effect
        statement.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>The presenter's graph and requirement are descriptive. They MUST NOT
      select issuer keys, accepted evidence types, revocation policy, or the
      assurance floor used for clearance.</t>
      <t>The evidence set MAY be represented as an Action Evidence Graph
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/>. Its same-action,
      relying-party-policy composition follows the Authorization Evidence Chain
      discipline <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain"/>;
      this profile adds the physical executor lifecycle and fixed initial
      evidence roles.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="action"><name>Model-to-Matter Action Object</name>
      <t>The initial Action Object version identifier is
      <tt>EP-MODEL-TO-MATTER-ACTION-v1</tt>. It is an I-JSON
      <xref target="RFC7493"/> object serialized with JCS
      <xref target="RFC8785"/>. Its action digest is
      <tt>"sha256:" || lowercase-hex(SHA-256(JCS(action)))</tt>.</t>
      <t>The initial <tt>action_type</tt> is
      <tt>science.bio.experiment.execute.1</tt>, registered by the CAID
      package. The executor MUST also compute the
      <tt>jcs-sha256</tt> Canonical Action Identifier (CAID)
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-canonical-action-identifier"/> over the same
      closed Action Object. The CAID's base64url digest component and the
      hexadecimal <tt>action_digest</tt> MUST decode to the same SHA-256
      octets. A mismatch is a refusal. CAID supplies portable content identity
      only; it does not establish identity, authority, authorization,
      execution, safety, or legal reliance.</t>
      <t>The initial profile requires these members:</t>
      <table>
        <thead><tr><th>Member</th><th>Required binding</th></tr></thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td><tt>@version</tt></td><td>The version identifier above.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>action_type</tt></td><td><tt>science.bio.experiment.execute.1</tt>.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>model</tt></td><td>Provider and model identifiers plus manifest, harness, and safeguards digests.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>experiment</tt></td><td>Protocol digest, material commitment, and expected-effects digest.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>principal</tt></td><td>Organization and principal identifiers.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>executor</tt></td><td>Executor and facility identifiers.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>purpose</tt></td><td>Purpose code and jurisdiction.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>destination_digest</tt></td><td>A digest of the intended destination representation.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>requested_at</tt></td><td>An RFC 3339 <xref target="RFC3339"/> instant.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>max_executions</tt></td><td>The integer <tt>1</tt>.</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>Unknown members MUST be rejected by this version. Portable objects
      MUST NOT contain raw sequences, raw protocols, prompts, completions,
      hidden reasoning, or equivalent sensitive source content. Such content
      remains in the source systems; only agreed digests or hiding commitments
      cross this boundary. A plain digest of low-entropy material is not a
      hiding commitment and MUST NOT be represented as one.</t>
      <t>The executor MUST compute the Action Object from the operation it will
      perform. It MUST NOT accept a presenter-supplied digest as a substitute
      for independently constructing and hashing the action.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="profile"><name>Relying-Party Profile</name>
      <t>The initial profile version identifier is
      <tt>EP-MODEL-TO-MATTER-PROFILE-v1</tt>. A profile binds:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>a stable <tt>profile_id</tt> and equal <tt>policy_id</tt>;</li>
        <li>the reliance purpose <tt>frontier_science_execution</tt>;</li>
        <li>the complete required evidence expression;</li>
        <li>allowed action types;</li>
        <li>a required human-assurance value;</li>
        <li>per-type freshness limits;</li>
        <li>the evidence types for which explicit revocation state is required;</li>
        <li>accepted pairs of issuer identity and public key for each evidence type; and</li>
        <li>a non-disableable same-action-agreement requirement.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The initial human-assurance wire values are <tt>software</tt>,
      <tt>class_a</tt>, and <tt>quorum</tt>, corresponding to software evidence,
      a device user-verified human, and a quorum of distinct device-verified
      humans. An implementation MUST reject unregistered values, including
      <tt>class_b</tt>. A physical-execution profile SHOULD require at least
      <tt>class_a</tt>; policy determines when a quorum is required.</t>
      <t>The profile MUST be provisioned through a relying-party-controlled
      channel. A profile or key registry received with presenter evidence MUST
      NOT be used to authorize that presentation.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="evidence"><name>Normalized Evidence Artifacts</name>
      <t>The initial evidence version identifier is
      <tt>EP-MODEL-TO-MATTER-EVIDENCE-v1</tt>. An evidence artifact contains
      <tt>evidence_type</tt>, <tt>action_digest</tt>, <tt>issuer_id</tt>,
      <tt>issued_at</tt>, <tt>expires_at</tt>, a closed <tt>claims</tt> object,
      an optional outcome, and a signature envelope.</t>
      <t>The initial profile requires exactly one accepted artifact of every
      following type:</t>
      <table>
        <thead><tr><th>Evidence type</th><th>Minimum same-action claims</th></tr></thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td><tt>model_attestation</tt></td><td>Provider, model, manifest, harness, and safeguards.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>safety_case_attestation</tt></td><td>Model commitments, safety-case digest, and assessment.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>institutional_authority</tt></td><td>Organization, principal, action family, purpose, and decision.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>biosafety_review</tt></td><td>Protocol, material commitment, facility, and decision.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>domain_screening</tt></td><td>Material commitment, destination, screening-profile digest, and decision.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><tt>human_authorization</tt></td><td>Approver, decision, and assurance evidence.</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>These names identify evidence roles, not authorities owned by this
      specification. For example, a <tt>domain_screening</tt> artifact reports
      what an accepted screening issuer signed; the Model-to-Matter verifier
      performs no screening itself.</t>
      <t>The initial signature algorithm is Ed25519 <xref target="RFC8032"/>.
      The signed bytes are the UTF-8 encoding of the version identifier,
      followed by one zero byte, followed by JCS of the artifact without its
      signature member. Each artifact MUST bind the exact action digest. The
      relying party MUST first verify the signature and then separately decide
      whether the exact <tt>(issuer_id, public_key)</tt> pair is accepted for
      that evidence type.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="challenge"><name>Registered Challenge</name>
      <t>The executor creates and durably registers a challenge binding the
      server-computed action digest, the profile digest, a nonce, the required
      evidence types, and an expiry. The challenge construction may use the
      Authorization Evidence Challenge mechanism
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-authorization-evidence-challenge"/>.</t>
      <t>Challenge state MUST provide atomic first-presentation consumption
      across all executor replicas. Storage unavailability, rollback, or an
      ambiguous consumption result MUST yield refusal. An implementation MUST
      NOT fall back to process-local state. At the clearance API boundary,
      storage exceptions and ambiguous consume results MUST be mapped to
      <tt>do_not_execute_refused</tt>; they MUST NOT escape as an untyped result
      that a caller could mistake for authorization.</t>
      <t>A missing-evidence refusal MAY include a new registered challenge that
      names only the missing types. A follow-up challenge is a new transaction;
      it does not reopen the consumed challenge.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="evaluation"><name>Clearance Evaluation</name>
      <t>An executor evaluating a presentation MUST perform these steps in
      order:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Clone or otherwise snapshot the action, profile, challenge, and
        evidence graph before the first asynchronous operation.</li>
        <li>Validate the closed object shapes and resource bounds.</li>
        <li>Recompute the action digest, CAID, and profile digest, and require
        the CAID and action digest to encode the same SHA-256 result.</li>
        <li>Require the challenge bindings and current time to match.</li>
        <li>Require an explicit revocation view for every profile-required
        evidence type. Absence of revocation state is not proof of
        non-revocation.</li>
        <li>Atomically consume the challenge.</li>
        <li>Verify each artifact's signature, issuer identity and role-scoped
        key pin, time window, revocation state, same-action binding, and
        type-specific claims.</li>
        <li>Require exactly the evidence types named by the relying-party
        profile and reject duplicate or unknown nodes.</li>
        <li>If and only if all checks pass, atomically consume
        <tt>"model-to-matter:" || action_caid</tt> in a durable shared store.</li>
        <li>Return <tt>clear_to_execute</tt> only when the action consumption is
        the first successful consumption. Every other outcome is a refusal.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>The initial clearance version identifier is
      <tt>EP-MODEL-TO-MATTER-CLEARANCE-v1</tt>. Its closed verdict set includes
      <tt>clear_to_execute</tt>, <tt>do_not_execute_missing_evidence</tt>,
      <tt>do_not_execute_stale_evidence</tt>,
      <tt>do_not_execute_conflicted</tt>,
      <tt>do_not_execute_unverifiable</tt>,
      <tt>do_not_execute_action_mismatch</tt>,
      <tt>do_not_execute_refused</tt>, and
      <tt>do_not_execute_malformed</tt>. Unknown verdicts MUST be treated as
      refusal.</t>
      <t>An action-bound clearance carries both <tt>action_digest</tt> and
      <tt>action_caid</tt>. The executor computes both fields; a presenter MUST
      NOT supply either value as a substitute for the Action Object.</t>
      <t>Consumption of the action digest MUST be non-expiring for as long as
      the action can be presented. An unavailable response after consumption
      is an indeterminate outcome that requires reconciliation. The executor
      MUST return <tt>do_not_execute_refused</tt>, mark reconciliation as
      required, and freeze execution; availability MUST NOT silently become a
      second clearance. After an indeterminate storage outcome, the enforcing
      executor MUST remain fail-stop and MUST NOT issue another challenge or
      evaluate another presentation until an operator has reconciled the
      durable challenge and action-consumption state.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="http"><name>HTTP Integration</name>
      <t>An HTTP executor MAY use status code 428 (Precondition Required)
      <xref target="RFC6585"/> to return the registered evidence challenge when
      clearance is absent. A client that cannot satisfy the challenge remains
      unable to invoke the physical effect. HTTP transport does not replace the
      atomic challenge and action stores.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="effect"><name>Executor Effect Statement</name>
      <t>After an execution attempt, the executor MAY sign an
      <tt>EP-MODEL-TO-MATTER-EFFECT-v1</tt> statement containing the action
      digest, action CAID, clearance replay digest, executor identity,
      execution time, status, and observed-effect digest. The statement MUST bind a prior
      <tt>clear_to_execute</tt> clearance for the same action and MUST verify
      under a relying-party-pinned executor key.</t>
      <t>Valid statuses are <tt>completed</tt>, <tt>failed</tt>, and
      <tt>aborted</tt>. The statement establishes only that the pinned executor
      signed those claims. It does not establish sensor integrity, causal
      attribution, or physical truth.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security"><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>Executor bypass.</strong> Model-to-Matter is effective only when
      every path to the protected effect traverses the enforcing executor.
      Alternate instruments, privileged maintenance paths, or direct backend
      access remain part of the trusted computing base.</t>
      <t><strong>Presenter-selected policy.</strong> Verifier code, issuer keys,
      profiles, revocation rules, and requirements MUST be pinned before a
      transaction. Accepting them beside evidence lets a presenter define the
      proof that its own evidence must pass.</t>
      <t><strong>Cross-action splicing.</strong> Every evidence artifact,
      challenge, clearance, consumption key, and effect statement MUST bind the
      executor-computed action digest. Clearances and effect statements MUST
      also bind the recomputed CAID, and both identifiers MUST name the same
      canonical bytes. A valid artifact for a different action is unsatisfied.</t>
      <t><strong>Issuer laundering.</strong> A signature proves control of a key,
      not authority for an evidence role. Acceptance MUST bind both issuer
      identity and key independently for each evidence type. A key accepted for
      one role MUST NOT satisfy another.</t>
      <t><strong>Replay and ambiguous effects.</strong> Challenge consumption
      prevents replay of one presentation; action-digest consumption prevents
      separately minted challenges from clearing the same action. Both stores
      require atomic shared state. After the effect begins, an unavailable
      response MUST leave the action consumed or frozen.</t>
      <t><strong>Revocation completeness.</strong> An empty or absent revocation
      view is not evidence that nothing is revoked. This profile requires an
      explicit view, but the authenticity, freshness, and completeness of that
      view remain deployment responsibilities unless a separately verifiable
      revocation mechanism is used.</t>
      <t><strong>Human authorization.</strong> A human evidence artifact is only
      as strong as credential enrollment, authenticator custody, user
      verification, and the presentation shown to the approver. A signature
      does not prove that the human understood the action.</t>
      <t><strong>Substantive judgment.</strong> Cryptography cannot prove that a
      model is safe, a review is correct, screening is complete, an action is
      lawful, or a physical result is benign. This profile MUST NOT be deployed
      as the sole control for a safety-critical physical effect. Independent
      technical, organizational, and operational controls remain necessary.</t>
      <t><strong>Resource exhaustion.</strong> Implementations MUST bound object
      depth, node count, string bytes, evidence count, identifier length, and
      parser work before signature or graph evaluation.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy"><name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>Action, evidence, and effect objects can reveal model use, institution,
      facility, principal, approver, purpose, destination, and timing. Profiles
      SHOULD minimize identifiers and use pairwise or pseudonymous values when
      accountability requirements permit. Logs require retention and access
      controls appropriate to their jurisdiction.</t>
      <t>Digests do not automatically provide confidentiality. Low-entropy or
      enumerable inputs can be recovered by guessing. Deployments handling
      sensitive material SHOULD use domain-separated hiding commitments with
      adequate randomness and keep openings outside portable evidence.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. A future revision may request media
      types or registries after the object model and deployment experience have
      stabilized.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="implementation"><name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>An Apache-2.0 JavaScript reference implementation, a synthetic
      self-checking demonstration, and adversarial tests are publicly
      available. The implementation covers the Action Object, profile, six
      signed evidence adapters, registered challenge, evidence graph,
      single-use clearance, and effect statement. A deterministic public suite
      exercises 15 CAID, acceptance, refusal, replay, storage-failure, and
      effect cases; 41 focused tests and a mutation-score floor exercise the reference
      implementation. It has no Python or Go port, no wet-lab deployment, no
      external scientific validation, and no claimed partnership or
      endorsement. The demonstration does not process raw biological content
      or perform screening.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8032.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-canonical-action-identifier" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier/">
        <front>
          <title>The Canonical Action Identifier (CAID)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-authorization-evidence-challenge" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-authorization-evidence-challenge/">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Evidence Challenge</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-authorization-evidence-challenge-00"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6585.xml"/>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph/">
        <front>
          <title>Action Evidence Graphs and Evidence Policy Replay for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain/">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Evidence Chains: Composing Heterogeneous Agent-Authorization Receipts</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-03"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
