<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-architecture-02"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EP Architecture">The EMILIA Protocol: An Evidence Architecture for Consequential Agent Actions</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-architecture-02"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal><country>US</country></postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="27"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <keyword>agent authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>cross-domain</keyword>
    <keyword>consequence control</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Consequential agent actions can cross operator and administrative
      boundaries. The party that later decides whether to rely on an action
      record may not have participated in the interaction and may not trust
      either operator. This document describes an evidence architecture for
      that case. It separates transport and workload identity, delegation and
      policy, material action identity, authorization evidence, evidence
      satisfaction, local authorization, durable consumption or reservation,
      effect invocation, outcome evidence, revocation, and preservation.</t>
      <t>The architecture composes the Canonical Action Identifier (CAID),
      Authorization Evidence Chain (AEC), and Action Evidence Boundary (AEB)
      with optional staged-approval and consequence-control profiles. It does
      not define a universal token, policy language, execution engine,
      settlement network, or distributed consensus system. A valid signature,
      a current credential, a satisfied evidence requirement, and an observed
      effect remain different facts.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>An agent in one administrative domain can request a gateway in
      another domain to perform an action whose consequences are borne by a
      third party. Months later, an auditor, counterparty, insurer, or
      regulator may need to determine which identity, delegation, policy,
      approval, consumption, invocation, and outcome facts held for that exact
      action. An operator-controlled log can be useful operationally, but it is
      not by itself portable evidence against a dishonest or unavailable
      operator.</t>
      <t>This architecture addresses that cross-domain and delayed-review
      case. It is not required for every agent interaction. A deployment in
      one trusted administrative domain, with no need to export or preserve
      independently verifiable evidence, can use ordinary authentication,
      authorization, and logging.</t>
      <t>The architecture defines a narrow waist. Native artifact verifiers
      establish artifact-specific facts. CAID correlates material action
      content. AEC evaluates whether a relying-party requirement is satisfied.
      Local policy decides whether to authorize. AEB controls the transition
      from evidence to a consequential effect and retains uncertainty when an
      effect cannot yet be proved or disproved. Optional profiles can add
      staged approvals, bounded capability state, receipt-program execution,
      escrow-controlled release, attestation, witnesses, or domain-specific
      bindings without changing the meaning of the core decisions.</t>
      <section anchor="applicability">
        <name>Applicability</name>
        <t>The architecture is useful when at least one of the following is
        true:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>the requester, executor, consequence owner, and later relying
          party are not all in one trust domain;</li>
          <li>an action can move money, change infrastructure, disclose
          protected data, create a legal or operational commitment, or cause a
          physical effect;</li>
          <li>authorization evidence must be verified after the live channel
          or originating operator is unavailable;</li>
          <li>one-time use, a budget, a deadline, staged approval, or
          separation of duties must be enforced across retries or replicas;
          or</li>
          <li>a provider can perform an effect and then fail to return a
          definitive response.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The architecture does not make a low-risk interaction
        consequential merely because an agent is involved.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
        capitals, as shown here.</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Native verifier:</dt>
          <dd>The verifier defined by an artifact's own specification,
          operating under trust anchors selected by the relying party.</dd>
          <dt>Relying party:</dt>
          <dd>The party that states an evidence requirement and decides
          whether to act on the verified facts.</dd>
          <dt>Consequential action:</dt>
          <dd>An action for which a deployment requires evidence and
          consequence controls that survive beyond the live interaction or
          operator boundary.</dd>
          <dt>Effect boundary:</dt>
          <dd>The point after which an external effect may have occurred and a
          transport failure can no longer safely be interpreted as no effect.</dd>
          <dt>Consequence owner:</dt>
          <dd>The one configured state machine responsible for claiming,
          invoking, and recording the outcome of a protected external effect.</dd>
          <dt>Trust Program:</dt>
          <dd>An optional relying-party-controlled orchestration profile in
          which verified evidence fills ordered or thresholded stages before
          one consequence owner can receive a fenced execution claim. Some
          implementations use the term Authority Program for the same pattern.</dd>
          <dt>Receipt Program:</dt>
          <dd>An optional consequence-owner profile that freezes one
          CAID-bound instruction, executes through a configured Gate, and
          emits a terminal certificate only after the Gate outcome and
          evidence-log transition succeed.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="vocabulary">
      <name>Decision and Lifecycle Vocabulary</name>
      <t>Conforming descriptions and APIs MUST keep the following states
      distinct:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>VERIFIED:</dt>
        <dd>An artifact passed its native cryptographic and structural
        verification under relying-party-selected trust anchors. It does not
        follow that the artifact filled an authorization role.</dd>
        <dt>MATCH:</dt>
        <dd>Two independently verified artifacts refer to the same material
        action, either by direct CAID equality or by an explicit, pinned
        mapping profile. MATCH is content correlation, not authorization.</dd>
        <dt>SATISFIED:</dt>
        <dd>The verified and matched evidence fills every slot in a
        relying-party-pinned evidence requirement. AEC can compute this state.</dd>
        <dt>AUTHORIZED:</dt>
        <dd>The relying party's local policy permits an attempted execution.
        This is a business and policy decision; no presented artifact
        establishes its own authority.</dd>
        <dt>RESERVED or CONSUMED:</dt>
        <dd>Durable state has fenced the operation's one-time authority,
        capability budget, or equivalent right before provider entry. This is
        not evidence that an effect occurred.</dd>
        <dt>INVOKED:</dt>
        <dd>The consequence owner durably records that provider entry has
        begun or may have begun. From this point, an exception or missing
        response cannot safely reopen authority.</dd>
        <dt>EXECUTED:</dt>
        <dd>Authenticated outcome evidence establishes that the bound effect
        occurred. This is distinct from what was requested or authorized.</dd>
        <dt>FAILED:</dt>
        <dd>Authenticated outcome evidence establishes that the bound effect
        did not occur or was definitively refused. A transport exception after
        provider entry is not sufficient for this state.</dd>
        <dt>INDETERMINATE:</dt>
        <dd>The effect may have occurred but current evidence establishes
        neither EXECUTED nor FAILED. Blind replay is unsafe.</dd>
        <dt>RECONCILED:</dt>
        <dd>Authenticated provider or system-of-record evidence resolves an
        INDETERMINATE operation to EXECUTED or to a proved-no-effect result.
        Reconciliation does not invoke the effect again.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>An implementation MUST NOT promote VERIFIED to MATCH, MATCH to
      SATISFIED, SATISFIED to AUTHORIZED, AUTHORIZED to RESERVED or CONSUMED,
      RESERVED or CONSUMED to INVOKED, or INVOKED to a terminal outcome
      without performing the separate check and durable transition that step
      requires.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="invariants">
      <name>Architectural Invariants</name>
      <section anchor="rp-inputs">
        <name>Relying-Party-Controlled Trust Inputs</name>
        <t>Trust anchors, verifier profiles, role assignments, evidence
        requirements, CAID mapping profiles, freshness limits, revocation
        policy, clocks, consumption stores, consequence owners, and outcome
        verifiers are relying-party inputs. They MUST NOT be selected or
        weakened by the artifact being judged or by transaction-scoped
        requester input.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="native-first">
        <name>Native Verification Before Correlation</name>
        <t>An artifact MUST pass its native verifier before any label, digest,
        or claimed relationship from that artifact is used for CAID matching
        or evidence satisfaction. A CAID does not repair an invalid native
        signature, an untrusted issuer, a stale credential, or an invalid
        native policy result.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="single-action">
        <name>One Material Action Across the Chain</name>
        <t>The action presented for approval, the action selected by local
        policy, the action used for capability reservation, the action passed
        to the consequence owner, and the action named by outcome evidence
        MUST resolve to the same CAID or to a mapping result accepted under one
        exact relying-party-pinned profile. Missing, lossy, or ambiguous
        mappings are INDETERMINATE and cannot establish MATCH.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="durable-state">
        <name>Durable State Before Effect</name>
        <t>When a deployment requires one-time use, a budget, staged approval,
        or no-blind-retry behavior, the authoritative state transition MUST be
        durable and atomic across replicas before provider entry. Process-local
        state is suitable only for explicit test or demonstration profiles.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="uncertainty">
        <name>Uncertainty Is Retained</name>
        <t>Before provider dispatch, the consequence owner MUST durably record
        enough invocation intent that recovery can distinguish an uninvoked
        operation from one that may have crossed the effect boundary. On
        restart, any operation for which provider entry cannot be disproved
        MUST become or remain INDETERMINATE. It MUST NOT silently return to an
        executable state.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="complete-mediation">
        <name>Complete Mediation</name>
        <t>The architecture controls only paths that traverse the configured
        enforcement point and consequence owner. A valid evidence chain or
        program state cannot prevent an administrator, alternate API, direct
        credential, or external payment path from bypassing that control.
        Non-bypassability is a deployment property.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="layers">
      <name>Layered Composition</name>
      <section anchor="identity">
        <name>Transport, Workload, Agent, and Human Identity</name>
        <t>This layer establishes who or what is present in a live channel,
        how a workload or agent credential is managed, and which human or
        organization a relying party has bound to a key. WIMSE and related
        workload-identity work are examples. The evidence architecture
        consumes those results but does not redefine them.</t>
        <t>A current credential answers an identity or status question. It
        does not by itself prove that its subject authorized one exact action,
        that a human rather than an agent operated the key, or that local
        policy permits the consequence.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="authority">
        <name>Delegation, Capability, and Policy</name>
        <t>This layer establishes what a principal delegated, what a
        capability permits, and what a policy decision point allowed. OAuth
        profiles, delegation artifacts, AuthZEN, and agent transport work
        occupy parts of this layer. A machine policy decision is not
        represented as human approval unless a separately defined and
        verified approval artifact establishes that fact.</t>
        <t>A bounded capability combines an immutable signed grant with
        mutable shared state. Receipt verification establishes the grant;
        action-scope matching and an atomic reserve/commit transition establish
        whether one operation can consume part of its budget. A signed budget
        without one authoritative state domain cannot enforce aggregate spend
        across replicas.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="action">
        <name>Material Action Identity and Mapping</name>
        <t>CAID <xref target="CAID"/> names typed material action content.
        Direct equality is byte-level content equality under the selected CAID
        suite. Cross-format comparison requires an Action-Mapping Profile
        selected and pinned by the relying party. A CAID carries no identity,
        authorization, capability, execution, or outcome semantics.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="artifacts">
        <name>Authorization and Confirmation Evidence</name>
        <t>This layer carries evidence that a specified approval ceremony or
        authorization event occurred. EMILIA authorization receipts
        <xref target="EP-RECEIPTS"/>, multi-party quorum records
        <xref target="EP-QUORUM"/>, and other confirmation artifacts can
        occupy this layer under their own guarantees. No single artifact is
        assumed to fill every relying-party requirement.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="satisfaction">
        <name>Evidence Composition and Satisfaction</name>
        <t>AEC <xref target="EP-AEC"/> verifies each component using the
        component's native verifier and role-scoped trust anchors, checks that
        all required components MATCH the same material action, and evaluates
        a relying-party-pinned requirement. Its result is SATISFIED or
        UNSATISFIED, not a universal authorization decision and not an
        execution result.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="orchestration">
        <name>Optional Staged Trust Programs</name>
        <t>A Trust Program can require several evidence stages, including
        ordered dependencies, heterogeneous thresholds, and separation of
        duties. Each stage consumes bounded results from registered native
        verifiers and can issue a signed stage receipt bound to the program,
        action, stage policy, predecessor receipts, and accepted evidence.</t>
        <t>A passing stage proves only that the configured technical evidence
        rule was satisfied. It does not upgrade weak native evidence, prove
        civil identity, or make an action lawful. A completed Trust Program
        can fence one claim for one selected consequence owner; it does not
        perform the external effect. This document defines the architectural
        role, not a Trust Program wire format.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="aeb">
        <name>Action Evidence Boundary</name>
        <t>AEB <xref target="EP-AEB"/> joins native verification, CAID MATCH,
        AEC SATISFIED, local AUTHORIZED, durable reservation or consumption,
        provider invocation, closed outcomes, and authenticated
        reconciliation. AEB is a lifecycle and enforcement boundary; it is not
        another receipt, credential, universal policy language, or evidence
        registry.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="outcome">
        <name>Outcome, Revocation, and Preservation</name>
        <t>Outcome evidence states what occurred after the effect boundary.
        Revocation states that named authority or evidence is no longer valid
        from an effective time. Preservation mechanisms retain verifiability
        as systems, operators, and algorithms change. Each answers a separate
        question, and none is inferred from receipt validity.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="profiles">
        <name>Application and Consequence Profiles</name>
        <t>Profiles select action types, evidence requirements, trust anchors,
        freshness, consumption, consequence ownership, outcome, and
        reconciliation rules for one deployment context. Agent gateways,
        payments, healthcare, infrastructure, and physical systems can use the
        architecture without changing the core artifact formats. A profile
        does not make a domain claim true; it states the checks and mediation
        boundary a deployment will apply.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="flow">
      <name>End-to-End Verification and Consequence Flow</name>
      <figure>
        <name>Non-collapsing action lifecycle</name>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 native artifacts
       |
       v
 VERIFIED -> MATCH -> SATISFIED -> AUTHORIZED
                                      |
                             reserve or consume
                                      |
                                      v
                             RESERVED / CONSUMED
                                      |
                        record invocation intent
                                      |
                                      v
                                  INVOKED
                                /    |    \
                               /     |     \
                       EXECUTED   FAILED   INDETERMINATE
                                             |
                              authenticated reconcile
                                             |
                              executed or proved-no-effect
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <ol spacing="normal">
        <li>The relying party derives the proposed action from
        executor-controlled facts and pins trust roots, verifier profiles,
        CAID suites or mapping profiles, evidence requirements, freshness,
        revocation policy, and the consequence owner.</li>
        <li>Each identity, delegation, policy, and approval artifact is
        verified by its native verifier. Presenter-supplied keys or labels do
        not create authority.</li>
        <li>Verified artifacts are matched to the exact action. Missing or
        lossy mappings yield INDETERMINATE and fail a required MATCH.</li>
        <li>AEC evaluates the evidence requirement. A missing role, mismatched
        action, stale fact, invalid signature, or unpinned trust anchor yields
        UNSATISFIED with a reproducible reason.</li>
        <li>An optional Trust Program admits the bounded native results into
        one or more stages. Otherwise, the relying party proceeds directly to
        local policy.</li>
        <li>The local enforcement point decides whether the satisfied evidence
        is sufficient to authorize an attempted execution.</li>
        <li>The authoritative state store atomically reserves or consumes the
        operation before provider entry. Failure to durably fence the
        operation is a refusal.</li>
        <li>The consequence owner durably records invocation intent and then
        invokes the provider. Recovery MUST conservatively classify a stranded
        operation as INDETERMINATE unless non-entry is established.</li>
        <li>Authenticated owner or provider evidence records EXECUTED, FAILED,
        or INDETERMINATE. An exception after possible provider entry is
        INDETERMINATE, not a refund or retry grant.</li>
        <li>Authenticated reconciliation can resolve INDETERMINATE without
        invoking the action again. Evidence records, revocation statements,
        and preservation artifacts remain separate, linked records.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="programs">
      <name>Programs and Multi-Stage Authorization</name>
      <section anchor="trust-program">
        <name>Trust Program</name>
        <t>A Trust Program addresses approvals in which one rule cannot be
        reduced to a single signature or a flat M-of-N quorum. A program can
        require, for example, a department approval followed by a compliance
        approval, with a later finance stage unlocked only by signed receipts
        from both predecessors. Each stage binds the same root CAID and action
        digest plus the exact predecessor stage-receipt digests.</t>
        <t>Stage thresholds apply to heterogeneous evidence seats. A native
        human quorum remains one natively verified quorum component; a Trust
        Program MUST NOT decompose several unverified labels and relabel them a
        quorum. Likewise, a stage receipt MUST NOT be treated as execution
        evidence.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="receipt-program">
        <name>Receipt Program</name>
        <t>A Receipt Program addresses a different problem: executing one
        already authorized and bounded instruction. A reference profile can
        bind the exact instruction, CAID, stable operation identifier,
        capability projection, executor selector, deadline, and result
        projection; call the configured Gate's reserve-before-effect path; and
        issue a terminal certificate over the resulting step sequence and
        linked Gate evidence.</t>
        <t>A Receipt Program is not an approval workflow, a smart contract, or
        proof that the external result is true. Its certificate is no stronger
        than the configured Gate, consequence owner, signer custody, evidence
        log, outcome evidence, and non-bypassability of the provider path.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ownership">
        <name>Single Consequence Ownership</name>
        <t>For one operation, exactly one configured consequence owner is
        responsible for provider entry and effect-outcome state. A Trust
        Program may select a Receipt Program or an Action Escrow release
        profile as that owner, but the two MUST NOT recursively claim or
        execute the same effect. Selection, claim, invocation, and outcome are
        separate transitions.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="consequence-profiles">
      <name>Optional Consequence-Control Profiles</name>
      <section anchor="bounded-capability">
        <name>Bounded Capability</name>
        <t>Bounded Capability Receipts <xref target="EP-BOUNDED"/> describe a
        signed exact-scope grant plus durable mutable state for registration,
        reservation, and commitment. The profile can limit amount, unit,
        currency, deadline, delegation, and operation identity. It does not
        define settlement, and signed bytes alone do not enforce a shared
        budget.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="action-escrow">
        <name>Action Escrow</name>
        <t>An Action Escrow profile can bind final agreement bytes, structured
        material terms, party roles, milestone evidence, exact release action,
        funding evidence, and a custodian result into one closed release state
        machine. A release is reserved before provider entry. An ambiguous
        provider result remains release-indeterminate until authenticated
        custodian reconciliation.</t>
        <t>Reference implementation experience exists for document binding,
        durable release state, evidence packaging, and bounded external
        adapters. That experience does not make EMILIA a custodian, escrow
        provider, settlement network, legal adjudicator, or source of truth for
        off-platform effects. Licensing, custody, solvency, legal
        enforceability, and provider finality remain outside this
        architecture.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dtc">
        <name>Distributed Trust Computer Deployment Pattern</name>
        <t>The term Distributed Trust Computer (DTC) is used by some
        implementations for a deployment pattern that composes action identity,
        authorization evidence, local policy, bounded authority, durable
        consequence control, terminal evidence, and optional independent
        witnesses or platform attestation. The distribution is of trust
        evidence and control roles; this architecture does not require a
        blockchain or consensus protocol.</t>
        <t>DTC is not a wire protocol defined by this document. The repository
        contains reference building blocks for several parts of the pattern,
        including Gate enforcement, CAID, AEC, bounded capabilities, Receipt
        Programs, Action Escrow, witness verification, and build-attestation
        verification. Their composition is not, by itself, evidence of a
        deployed DTC, independent operators, physical-hardware attestation,
        cross-vendor interoperability, or settlement finality.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="lifecycle">
      <name>Revocation, Disputes, and Compensating Actions</name>
      <section anchor="revocation">
        <name>Revocation and Current Status</name>
        <t>A portable revocation statement <xref target="EP-REVOCATION"/> can
        establish that a pinned revoker invalidated one exact target at an
        effective time. A pre-claim revocation can prevent new authority from
        advancing. A revocation learned after provider entry does not rewrite
        an effect as though it never happened.</t>
        <t>Possession of no revocation statement is not proof of current
        non-revocation. A relying party that requires current status needs a
        fresh authenticated status view with completeness and rollback
        properties appropriate to its deployment.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dispute">
        <name>Disputes</name>
        <t>A dispute records that a party contests an authorization, outcome,
        amount, quality, or other fact. Opening a dispute does not prove either
        side correct, revoke a credential, reverse an external effect, or grant
        authority for a remedy. Dispute evidence therefore remains separate
        from the original immutable action record.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="remedy">
        <name>Compensating Actions</name>
        <t>A return, refund, rollback, cancellation, or other remedy that
        creates an external effect is a new consequential action. It needs its
        own action object, CAID, authorization evidence, operation identifier,
        consequence owner, outcome, and reconciliation path. A remedy links to
        the original action but does not mutate it.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="components">
      <name>Component Boundaries and Implementation Status</name>
      <t>The following status descriptions are intentionally narrower than the
      architecture:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li><xref target="EP-RECEIPTS"/> defines an action-bound
        authorization evidence artifact and verification profiles. It is a
        published individual Internet-Draft, not an RFC or adopted standard.</li>
        <li><xref target="EP-QUORUM"/> composes distinct approval ceremonies
        for multi-party requirements. It is a published individual
        Internet-Draft.</li>
        <li><xref target="CAID"/> defines material action identity and
        profile-bounded matching. It grants no authority. It is a published
        individual Internet-Draft.</li>
        <li><xref target="EP-AEC"/> defines evidence composition and
        requirement satisfaction. It does not make the local authorization or
        execution decision. It is a published individual Internet-Draft.</li>
        <li><xref target="EP-BOUNDED"/> defines a signed grant plus durable
        reserve-execute-commit profile for scoped, budgeted multi-operation
        authority. It is a published experimental individual Internet-Draft.</li>
        <li><xref target="EP-AEB"/> defines the effect-boundary lifecycle and
        enforcement composition. At the time of this revision it is a
        companion individual-draft proposal, not an adopted standard.</li>
        <li><xref target="EP-REVOCATION"/> defines a portable terminal
        revocation statement. Its reference verifier and vectors provide
        implementation experience, but they do not prove availability or
        completeness of current status information.</li>
        <li>Gate enforcement, Receipt Programs, and Action Escrow have
        reference implementation profiles. A development Trust Program build
        supplies implementation experience for staged orchestration. This
        architecture does not standardize those APIs, claim independent
        implementations, or assert that any specific deployment completely
        mediates all consequential paths.</li>
        <li>DTC names a broader deployment pattern. It is not a protocol or a
        deployment claim in this document.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="related">
      <name>Relationship to Adjacent Work</name>
      <t>The architecture is designed to compose with, rather than absorb,
      adjacent work:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The DMSC Agent Gateway gap-analysis draft
        <xref target="DMSC-GW"/> provides concrete multi-domain and
        physical-action gateway scenarios. It is an individual draft, not a
        claim of IETF consensus.</li>
        <li>WIMSE Condition-Bounded Credentials <xref target="WIMSE-CBC"/>
        establish workload identity and channel-possession properties. They do
        not by themselves establish per-action human authorization.</li>
        <li>WIMSE HTTP Signatures <xref target="WIMSE-HTTP-SIG"/> protect
        selected end-to-end HTTP material. An AEB profile must distinguish
        signed end-to-end action fields from intermediary context that is
        legitimately mutable or removable.</li>
        <li>WIMSE Authorization Evidence <xref target="WIMSE-EVIDENCE"/>
        defines transport of authorization evidence in workload-mediated HTTP.
        AEC and AEB can consume such evidence through its native verifier
        without redefining the carrier.</li>
        <li>AuthZEN's Access Request and Approval Profile
        <xref target="AUTHZEN-AARP"/> defines asynchronous approval tasks and
        policy-decision-point re-evaluation. EMILIA profiles are complementary
        when a deployment requires portable exact-action evidence, distinct
        human ceremonies, durable consumption, or consequence reconciliation.
        Those properties are not implied by a generic approval result.</li>
        <li>FIDO Verifiable Intent <xref target="FIDO-VI"/> describes portable
        evidence of user intent. The cited page describes a contribution and
        prospective standardization, not a final FIDO specification.</li>
        <li>KLRC agent authentication <xref target="KLRC-AUTH"/> separates
        agent credentials and their lifecycle from application semantics.
        Credential validity and per-action authorization remain separate in
        this architecture.</li>
        <li>AGTP <xref target="AGTP"/> carries agent identity, authority,
        attribution, and application payloads at the wire layer. This
        architecture defines evidence that can be carried or referenced by
        that transport and checked after the live channel is gone.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The primary architectural failure is category collapse. A valid
      signature can authenticate an untrusted assertion; it does not make the
      assertion authoritative. A current credential does not prove a human
      approved one exact action. A policy ALLOW does not prove a named human
      approved. A matching CAID does not prove either artifact is valid. A
      satisfied evidence requirement does not prove an action is lawful, safe,
      wise, or correctly executed.</t>
      <t>Trust inputs MUST NOT be silently imported from the artifact being
      judged. Native verifier exceptions, missing trust configuration, stale
      status, store unavailability, signer failure, or ambiguous effects must
      fail closed while preserving a reason suitable for recovery and audit.</t>
      <t>Consumption and reservation state must resist replay, rollback,
      concurrent writers, replica divergence, operation relabeling, and caller
      mutation. A provider idempotency key reduces duplicate effects but does
      not replace local atomic state or authenticated reconciliation.</t>
      <t>Human evidence remains vulnerable to coercion, fatigue,
      mis-rendering, compromised devices, and collusion. Device-bound user
      verification, exact-action presentation, initiator exclusion, staged
      programs, and distinct-human quorum reduce specified threats but do not
      establish comprehension or correctness.</t>
      <t>Optional witness or platform-attestation evidence is bounded by the
      independence of operators, enrollment of keys, measured-build policy,
      freshness, and verifier correctness. A same-operator witness or software
      TPM fixture must not be described as independent or physical-hardware
      proof.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>Action objects and evidence chains can expose identities,
      relationships, amounts, destinations, medical or employment context,
      infrastructure topology, and business intent. CAID is a digest-based
      identifier, not an anonymization mechanism; low-entropy action spaces can
      permit guessing.</t>
      <t>Profiles SHOULD minimize portable fields, prefer pairwise identifiers
      where correlation is not required, separate evidence references from raw
      source records, define retention and disclosure policy, and avoid placing
      secrets or bearer claim tokens in logs. Selective-disclosure mechanisms
      do not remove the need to bind every disclosed projection to the exact
      action and relying-party requirement.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="operational">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>Production profiles need durable state, stable operation identifiers,
      clock monitoring, key custody, trust-root rotation, authenticated status
      and outcome sources, retention controls, and explicit recovery for
      INDETERMINATE operations. Test-only in-memory stores, generated keys,
      local witnesses, and software attestation fixtures must be visibly
      separated from production configuration.</t>
      <t>Operators SHOULD expose the distinct lifecycle verdicts and refusal
      reasons rather than one boolean "authorized" field. Monitoring SHOULD
      alert on repeated indeterminate outcomes, stale revocation views,
      reconciliation backlog, store conflicts, signer failures, and attempted
      bypass of the configured consequence owner.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="changes">
      <name>Changes from -01</name>
      <t>This revision:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>makes CAID, AEC, and AEB the explicit continuity core;</li>
        <li>extends the vocabulary with durable reservation, invocation,
        indeterminate outcome, and reconciliation states;</li>
        <li>adds the recovery invariant that possible provider entry cannot
        return silently to an executable state;</li>
        <li>adds optional staged Trust Programs and distinguishes them from
        Receipt Programs;</li>
        <li>defines single consequence ownership and profiles bounded
        capabilities, Receipt Programs, and Action Escrow without changing
        core artifact formats;</li>
        <li>describes DTC as a deployment pattern, not a deployed protocol or
        consensus system;</li>
        <li>clarifies pre-claim and late revocation, disputes, and compensating
        actions; and</li>
        <li>adds explicit implementation-status, privacy, and operational
        claim boundaries.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="CAID" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier/">
        <front>
          <title>The Canonical Action Identifier (CAID)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-AEC" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain/">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Evidence Chains: Composing Heterogeneous Agent-Action Evidence (EP-AEC)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-04"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-RECEIPTS" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-08"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-QUORUM" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-quorum/">
        <front>
          <title>Multi-Party Quorum Authorization for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-QUORUM)</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-quorum-03"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-BOUNDED" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-bounded-capability-receipts/">
        <front>
          <title>Bounded Capability Receipts and Durable Spend Control for Agent Actions</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-bounded-capability-receipts-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-AEB" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-action-evidence-boundary/">
        <front>
          <title>The Action Evidence Boundary for Consequential Agent Effects</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-action-evidence-boundary-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="EP-REVOCATION" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-revocation-statement/">
        <front>
          <title>Portable Revocation Statements for Action-Bound Authorization Artifacts</title>
          <author fullname="Iman Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-revocation-statement-00"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="DMSC-GW" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-dunbar-dmsc-gw-scenarios-gap-analysis/">
        <front>
          <title>Deployment Scenarios and Gap Analysis for AI Agent Gateway</title>
          <author fullname="Linda Dunbar"/>
          <author fullname="YiFei Wang"/>
          <author fullname="Bing Liu"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July" day="2"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-dunbar-dmsc-gw-scenarios-gap-analysis-02"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="WIMSE-CBC" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-winmagic-wimse-condition-bounded-credentials/">
        <front>
          <title>Condition-Bounded Credentials for Workload and Agent Identity: Non-Exfiltratable Keys and Validity by Presence</title>
          <author fullname="Thi Nguyen-Huu"/>
          <author fullname="Sergei Nikitin"/>
          <author fullname="John O'Leary"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-winmagic-wimse-condition-bounded-credentials-01"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="WIMSE-HTTP-SIG" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-wimse-http-signature/">
        <front>
          <title>WIMSE Workload-to-Workload Authentication with HTTP Signatures</title>
          <author fullname="Joseph A. Salowey"/>
          <author fullname="Yaron Sheffer"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-wimse-http-signature-05"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="WIMSE-EVIDENCE" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-munoz-wimse-authorization-evidence/">
        <front>
          <title>Signed Authorization-Evidence Records for WIMSE-Authorized AI Agent Actions</title>
          <author fullname="Christian Munoz"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-munoz-wimse-authorization-evidence-01"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="KLRC-AUTH" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-klrc-aiagent-auth/">
        <front>
          <title>AI Agent Authentication and Authorization</title>
          <author fullname="Pieter Kasselman"/>
          <author fullname="Jeff Lombardo"/>
          <author fullname="Yaroslav Rosomakho"/>
          <author fullname="Brian Campbell"/>
          <author fullname="Nick Steele"/>
          <author fullname="Aaron Parecki"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-klrc-aiagent-auth-03"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="AUTHZEN-AARP" target="https://openid.github.io/authzen/authzen-access-request-approval-profile-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>AuthZEN Access Request and Approval Profile - Draft 1</title>
          <author fullname="K. McGuinness"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July" day="9"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="FIDO-VI" target="https://fidoalliance.org/building-the-trust-layer-for-agentic-payments-with-ap2-and-verifiable-intent/">
        <front>
          <title>Building the Trust Layer for Agentic Payments with AP2 and Verifiable Intent</title>
          <author><organization>FIDO Alliance</organization></author>
          <date year="2026" month="May" day="26"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="AGTP" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-hood-independent-agtp/">
        <front>
          <title>Agent Transfer Protocol (AGTP)</title>
          <author fullname="Chris Hood"/>
          <date year="2026" month="June" day="28"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-hood-independent-agtp-09"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgments">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Eric Rescorla's review prompted a sharper separation between
      baseline verifier security properties and the specific need for
      third-party, cross-domain validation. Linda Dunbar's Agent Gateway
      scenarios supplied a concrete multi-operator use case. Discussion of
      WIMSE signatures and authorization evidence sharpened the boundary
      between end-to-end signed material and mutable intermediary context.
      Work on agent credentials, authorization transports, and agent transfer
      helped clarify why identity, policy, action evidence, execution, and
      outcome remain separate. These acknowledgments do not imply endorsement
      of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
