<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-action-evidence-boundary-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Action Evidence Boundary">The Action Evidence Boundary for Consequential Agent Effects</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-action-evidence-boundary-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="27"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>effect boundary</keyword>
    <keyword>replay prevention</keyword>
    <keyword>reconciliation</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Consequential agent actions can cross identity, transport,
      authorization, policy, and execution systems. Each system can produce a
      valid artifact while the executor still lacks a safe rule for joining
      the artifacts to the exact effect, consuming one-time authority, and
      handling an uncertain outcome. This document defines the Action
      Evidence Boundary (AEB), an executor-side processing model for that
      lifecycle.</t>
      <t>AEB requires native artifact verification, Canonical Action
      Identifier (CAID) matching, Authorization Evidence Chain (AEC)
      satisfaction, a separate local authorization decision, durable atomic
      consumption or reservation, invocation, closed effect outcomes, and
      authenticated reconciliation. It defines no receipt or token format,
      no policy language, no universal evidence taxonomy, and no new
      registry. Native workload credentials, message signatures, attested
      per-action tokens, permit records, authorization receipts, and status
      mechanisms retain their own semantics and verifiers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>A remote executor can receive several independently useful inputs:
      a workload credential and protected request, a delegation or capability,
      a pre-execution permit, a human-authorization artifact, and a policy
      decision. None of those inputs alone answers every question the
      consequence-owning system has to answer before changing its system of
      record.</t>
      <t>The missing contract is at the effect boundary. The executor must
      determine what exact material action it is about to perform; verify each
      artifact under its native rules; correlate independently verified
      representations without guessing; evaluate whether the evidence bundle
      fills its requirement; make its own authorization decision; consume or
      reserve any one-time or bounded authority; invoke the effect once; and
      preserve uncertainty when the effect cannot be observed conclusively.</t>
      <t>This document defines that contract. Its required order is:</t>
      <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
 native verification
        |
        v
 CAID material-action MATCH
        |
        v
 AEC evidence SATISFIED
        |
        v
 local policy AUTHORIZED
        |
        v
 atomic CONSUMED / RESERVED
        |
        v
 durable DISPATCH_PENDING
        |
        v
 INVOKED
        |
        +--> EXECUTED
        +--> FAILED
        +--> INDETERMINATE --> authenticated reconciliation
]]></artwork>
      <t>Every arrow is conditional. A signature is not authority. Native
      verification is not action correlation. Action correlation is not
      evidence satisfaction. Evidence satisfaction is not local
      authorization. Authorization is not execution. An invocation error is
      not proof that no effect occurred.</t>
      <section anchor="scope">
        <name>Scope and Non-Goals</name>
        <t>AEB specifies processing requirements for a boundary that controls
        a consequential effect. It can be implemented at a protocol gateway,
        service mesh component, application middleware, execution adapter, or
        system-of-record write path, provided the deployment states which
        effect paths the boundary actually mediates.</t>
        <t>AEB does not define:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>a new authorization receipt, access token, attestation token,
          permit, credential, or execution-evidence format;</li>
          <li>a native signature, credential, revocation, status, or
          transparency verification algorithm;</li>
          <li>a policy language, universal authorization decision, or
          universal human-approval inference;</li>
          <li>general semantic equivalence between actions;</li>
          <li>provider truth, physical truth, legality, safety, wisdom, or
          complete mediation merely because an AEB implementation is
          present; or</li>
          <li>a registry for evidence types, states, action mappings, or
          verifier names.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions">
      <name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Effect boundary:</dt>
        <dd>The last control point that can withhold the protected mutation
        before it is submitted to the effecting system.</dd>
        <dt>Relying party:</dt>
        <dd>The party that selects trust inputs, action definitions, mapping
        profiles, evidence requirements, freshness rules, and local
        authorization policy, and that relies on the resulting decision.</dd>
        <dt>Native artifact:</dt>
        <dd>An evidence, credential, permit, token, receipt, status, or
        message-protection object defined outside AEB and verified under its
        own specification.</dd>
        <dt>Observed action:</dt>
        <dd>The immutable material action constructed by the effect boundary
        from executor-controlled parsing and system-of-record facts.</dd>
        <dt>Material field:</dt>
        <dd>A field whose change can alter the protected consequence, as
        declared by the selected CAID action-type definition.</dd>
        <dt>Invocation:</dt>
        <dd>The first dispatch of the frozen authorized action to a component
        that can cause the protected effect.</dd>
        <dt>Authoritative reconciliation:</dt>
        <dd>An authenticated, audience-bound observation from the effecting
        provider or system of record that is matched to the original action
        and operation identifier.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="vocabulary">
      <name>Non-Collapsing Decision and Lifecycle Vocabulary</name>
      <t>AEB uses the following decisions with the meanings established by
      the EMILIA architecture and its component drafts:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>VERIFIED:</dt>
        <dd>One native artifact passed its native verifier under
        relying-party-selected trust inputs.</dd>
        <dt>MATCH:</dt>
        <dd>Independently verified artifacts denote the same material action
        directly or under exact relying-party-pinned CAID mapping
        profiles.</dd>
        <dt>SATISFIED:</dt>
        <dd>Verified and matched evidence fills every slot in the relying
        party's AEC requirement.</dd>
        <dt>AUTHORIZED:</dt>
        <dd>The consequence-owning relying party's local policy permits this
        exact action at this time.</dd>
        <dt>EXECUTED:</dt>
        <dd>The executor records, or an accepted native artifact attests,
        that the exact effect occurred. This meaning remains bounded by the
        native source and its trust assumptions.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>AEB also names operational lifecycle states:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>CONSUMED:</dt>
        <dd>A one-time authorization, challenge, operation key, or equivalent
        native replay unit has been durably made unavailable for another
        invocation.</dd>
        <dt>RESERVED:</dt>
        <dd>Bounded state, such as a capability budget, has been durably
        fenced for the exact operation before invocation.</dd>
        <dt>DISPATCH_PENDING:</dt>
        <dd>A durable intent record binds the frozen action, operation
        identifier, provider environment, and reservation before any
        effecting dispatch can occur. Recovery treats a stranded intent as
        uncertain, not as unused authority.</dd>
        <dt>INVOKED:</dt>
        <dd>The protected effect was dispatched using the frozen authorized
        action and operation identifier.</dd>
        <dt>FAILED:</dt>
        <dd>Authoritative executor or reconciliation evidence establishes
        that the invoked operation did not cause the protected effect. A
        local exception or timeout alone is not sufficient.</dd>
        <dt>INDETERMINATE:</dt>
        <dd>Invocation began, but available authoritative evidence does not
        establish whether the protected effect occurred.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>CONSUMED, RESERVED, DISPATCH_PENDING, INVOKED, FAILED, and
      INDETERMINATE are lifecycle terms, not new evidence types or IANA
      registry values. A deployment MAY use different local labels if their
      semantics are at least as strict.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pins">
      <name>Relying-Party Inputs and Pins</name>
      <t>The requester, presenter, agent, and mutable intermediary context are
      untrusted inputs. They MAY propose an action and present native
      artifacts. They MUST NOT select or weaken the controls used to accept
      that request.</t>
      <t>Before evaluating an action, the relying party MUST configure or pin,
      as applicable:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>the supported native artifact revisions, verifier adapters,
        algorithms, trust anchors, issuers, audiences, and status sources;</li>
        <li>the CAID suite, action-type definition source, exact source
        descriptors, and mapping-profile digests;</li>
        <li>the AEC requirement and the admissible native evidence roles for
        each slot;</li>
        <li>local policy identifiers, policy epochs, tenant and organization
        boundaries, and any separation-of-duty rule;</li>
        <li>the trusted clock, maximum ages, validity windows, allowed skew,
        and revocation or status freshness requirements;</li>
        <li>the durable replay, consumption, reservation, and operation-key
        namespaces; and</li>
        <li>the protected executor, provider environment, reconciliation
        endpoint, and authenticated provider or system-of-record identities.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>A label, key, profile identifier, requirement, status assertion, or
      policy identifier carried only in presenter-controlled data MUST NOT
      become its own trust anchor. Missing, conflicting, unsupported, or
      ambiguous required configuration MUST fail closed.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="processing">
      <name>Required Processing Model</name>
      <section anchor="observe-action">
        <name>Construct the Observed Material Action</name>
        <t>The effect boundary MUST construct an immutable observed action
        from effect-relevant facts it controls. Depending on the application,
        those facts can include the protocol operation, tool or method,
        target resource, tenant, account, amount, currency, destination,
        environment, input digest, and unique operation identifier.</t>
        <t>The boundary MUST resolve a relying-party-pinned CAID action-type
        definition and include every field that definition declares material.
        It MUST NOT copy a requester-supplied action digest, CAID, amount,
        destination, or resource reference without deriving or checking the
        corresponding fact at the protected boundary. If the boundary cannot
        determine all material fields, it MUST refuse before invocation.</t>
        <t>The observed action MUST be frozen for the remainder of the
        lifecycle. A later adapter MUST NOT reconstruct a different action
        from mutable request state after authorization.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="native-verification">
        <name>Verify Each Native Artifact</name>
        <t>Each required native artifact MUST be verified independently under
        its own specification and relying-party-selected trust inputs before
        CAID mapping or AEC evaluation. The AEB implementation MUST use the
        integrity-protected payload returned by the native verifier, or a
        projection for which the adapter establishes integrity coverage of
        every projected field.</t>
        <t>A successful signature check is only one possible step of native
        verification. Schema, algorithm, issuer, audience, key status,
        validity, proof-of-possession, freshness, replay, and native policy
        checks remain those of the selected native profile. A verifier
        exception, unavailable required status source, unsupported critical
        field, or ambiguous result MUST become a bounded refusal, never an
        allow path.</t>
        <t>The output of this stage is VERIFIED for each accepted artifact.
        An artifact that has not reached VERIFIED MUST NOT participate in
        action mapping or fill an AEC requirement slot.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="caid-match">
        <name>Establish CAID Material-Action MATCH</name>
        <t>The boundary MUST recompute the CAID of the observed action under
        the selected suite and definition source. It MUST compare every
        action-bound required artifact to that observed action using direct
        CAID equality or the Action-Mapping Profile defined by
        <xref target="CAID"/>.</t>
        <t>Cross-format mapping MUST occur only after native verification and
        MUST use the exact source media type, schema version, target action
        type, definition source, and mapping-profile digest pinned by the
        relying party. Every target material field MUST be covered. Missing,
        lossy, unknown, unpinned, conflicting, or ambiguous mappings yield
        INDETERMINATE under CAID and MUST fail a required MATCH. AEB MUST NOT
        guess equivalence from names, natural-language descriptions, trace
        identifiers, or presenter assertions.</t>
        <t>MATCH is content correlation only. It does not validate a native
        artifact and does not authorize execution.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="aec-satisfaction">
        <name>Evaluate AEC Evidence Satisfaction</name>
        <t>The boundary MUST submit only natively verified, action-matched
        evidence to an AEC verifier configured with the relying party's
        requirement. The requirement used for the decision MUST come from
        relying-party configuration, not from a presenter-controlled AEC
        member.</t>
        <t>Every required evidence role MUST be filled by an artifact whose
        native verifier and adapter are accepted for that role. A workload
        identity MUST NOT silently fill a policy-permit or human-authorization
        slot. A machine-policy decision MUST NOT silently fill a named-human
        slot. A generic operator signature MUST NOT be interpreted as evidence
        that a human operated a system or performed a named approval ceremony.</t>
        <t>Only a successful AEC evaluation under these inputs reaches
        SATISFIED. UNSATISFIED, malformed, unsupported, or ambiguous results
        MUST withhold invocation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="local-authorization">
        <name>Make the Local Authorization Decision</name>
        <t>The consequence-owning executor MUST make a separate local
        authorization decision after SATISFIED. It MUST evaluate the exact
        observed action, audience, tenant, organization, policy epoch,
        freshness, current credential and authority status, separation of
        duties, local risk controls, and any bounded capability state.</t>
        <t>Credential revocation and per-action authorization evidence answer
        different questions. A current non-revocation or status result can
        establish that a credential remains acceptable under local policy; it
        does not prove that the credential holder authorized this action. A
        per-action authorization artifact does not prove that every credential
        in its trust path remains current. When policy requires both, the
        boundary MUST verify both without substituting one for the other.</t>
        <t>The boundary reaches AUTHORIZED only if local policy permits the
        exact action at the decision time. SATISFIED alone MUST NOT trigger
        reservation or invocation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="consume-reserve">
        <name>Atomically Consume or Reserve Before Invocation</name>
        <t>After AUTHORIZED and before invocation, the boundary MUST perform
        the durable state transition required by the native evidence and
        local policy. This can include consuming a one-time authorization,
        challenge nonce, or operation key; reserving a bounded capability or
        budget; and fencing the operation to one owner across replicas.</t>
        <t>The transition MUST be atomic within the relying party's durable
        state domain. Its key MUST be derived from verified evidence or the
        executor-owned observed action and operation identifier, never from a
        presenter-selected decoy. If the store is unavailable, non-atomic,
        stale, or reports an ambiguous result, the boundary MUST refuse before
        invocation.</t>
        <t>AEB does not claim atomicity between a local store and an unrelated
        remote provider. It requires the local consume or reserve transition
        to occur first so that any uncertainty after dispatch cannot make the
        same authority available for an uncontrolled second effect.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="invoke">
        <name>Invoke the Frozen Action</name>
        <t>Before any call, message, or byte can reach an effecting component,
        the boundary MUST durably enter DISPATCH_PENDING for the frozen
        observed action that reached AUTHORIZED and CONSUMED or RESERVED. The
        record MUST bind the action digest, operation identifier, provider
        environment, audience, reservation or consumption record, and
        adapter. Failure or ambiguity while writing this record MUST withhold
        dispatch.</t>
        <t>The boundary MUST invoke only from that durable state. It MUST use a
        stable, action-bound, unique operation identifier or idempotency key
        where the provider supports one. After dispatch begins, it MUST
        durably record INVOKED or a terminal outcome before reporting success
        to the requester.</t>
        <t>The adapter MUST receive only the authority and evidence necessary
        for the downstream interface. It MUST NOT accept mutable intermediary
        or caller context that changes a material field after the boundary's
        authorization decision.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="outcome">
        <name>Classify the Effect Outcome</name>
        <t>After invocation begins, the boundary MUST classify the result as
        EXECUTED, FAILED, or INDETERMINATE. On restart, a
        DISPATCH_PENDING operation without an authoritative terminal record
        MUST be promoted to INDETERMINATE before any retry or release, because
        the process cannot establish that dispatch did not begin.</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>EXECUTED requires an authoritative response or accepted native
          execution evidence matched to the exact action, operation
          identifier, provider environment, and audience.</li>
          <li>FAILED requires authoritative evidence that the invoked
          operation did not cause the protected effect. A local parse error,
          exception, timeout, connection loss, process crash, or missing
          response is not by itself such evidence.</li>
          <li>INDETERMINATE is REQUIRED whenever invocation may have reached
          the effecting system but the available authoritative evidence does
          not establish EXECUTED or FAILED.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>For EXECUTED, the boundary MUST commit any reserved spend and
        preserve the terminal evidence. For FAILED, it MUST preserve the
        failure evidence and follow the native reservation policy. For
        INDETERMINATE, it MUST preserve or consume the reservation, refuse
        reuse of the authorization and operation identifier, and prohibit a
        blind replay.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="reconcile">
        <name>Perform Authenticated Reconciliation</name>
        <t>An INDETERMINATE operation, including one recovered from a stranded
        DISPATCH_PENDING record, MUST remain closed until reconciliation
        authenticates the provider or system of record and matches the result
        to the original action, operation identifier, provider environment,
        audience, target resource, and every application-specific material
        field.</t>
        <t>Reconciliation MAY move INDETERMINATE to EXECUTED when
        authoritative evidence establishes that the exact effect occurred.
        It MAY move INDETERMINATE to FAILED when authoritative evidence
        establishes that it did not occur. Missing, stale, conflicting,
        unauthenticated, or action-mismatched observations MUST leave the
        operation INDETERMINATE.</t>
        <t>Reconciliation MUST NOT resurrect the original authorization or
        silently release its one-time replay unit. If policy permits a later
        attempt after an authoritative FAILED result, that attempt MUST use a
        new action instance and complete the lifecycle required by local
        policy. An implementation MUST NOT invoke again merely because a
        timeout elapsed or because the caller retried.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="declaration-challenge">
      <name>Declaration and Challenge Semantics</name>
      <t>A deployment MAY publish a static declaration describing protected
      actions, material fields, evidence requirements, challenge methods, and
      effect-boundary placement. Such a declaration is discovery metadata. It
      MUST NOT override the relying party's live, local enforcement
      configuration. An unsupported declaration version MUST be ignored as
      discovery input; it cannot weaken or replace live enforcement. An
      action that the live boundary configuration cannot classify or process
      under a supported version MUST fail closed.</t>
      <t>When required evidence is absent or unacceptable, a boundary MAY use
      its application protocol to return a dynamic challenge. A challenge
      MUST identify the boundary-computed action, the missing evidence roles,
      the policy context, an intended audience, a short expiry, and a
      single-use unpredictable nonce or equivalent replay unit. The nonce
      MUST NOT be consumed merely because untrusted bytes parse. It MUST be
      consumed atomically only after the selected native verifier establishes
      the integrity and challenge binding of an in-window presentation, and
      before that presentation can reach SATISFIED or authorize an effect.
      A presentation that is malformed, unauthenticated, expired, or not
      bound to the challenge MUST be refused without burning the nonce.
      A natively verified, challenge-bound presentation consumes the nonce
      whether or not the remaining evidence satisfies the requirement.
      Follow-up challenges MUST remain bound to the original boundary-computed
      action and MUST NOT derive that action from presenter input.</t>
      <t>A declaration or challenge authorizes nothing, reserves nothing, and
      promises no execution. A satisfied challenge still proceeds through
      native verification, MATCH, SATISFIED, local AUTHORIZED, and atomic
      consumption or reservation. This document intentionally defines no new
      manifest object, challenge object, well-known URI, HTTP status code, or
      media type.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="native-formats">
      <name>Native Evidence and Transport Boundaries</name>
      <section anchor="wimse-http">
        <name>WIMSE and HTTP Message Signatures</name>
        <t>WIMSE workload credentials and the WIMSE HTTP Message Signatures
        profile <xref target="WIMSE-HTTP"/> can provide end-to-end workload
        authentication and message integrity for the request components
        covered by the validated signature, including a body protected by a
        validated content digest. HTTP Message Signatures
        <xref target="RFC9421"/> provide the underlying component-signing
        mechanism.</t>
        <t>AEB consumes those results; it does not redefine them. A validated
        WIMSE request can establish which workload possessed the protected key
        and that covered message components were not modified undetectably. It
        does not by itself establish CAID MATCH, AEC SATISFIED, named-human
        authorization, local AUTHORIZED, one-time consumption, or execution.</t>
        <t>The AI Agent Authentication and Authorization framework
        <xref target="KLRC-AUTH"/> and the WIMSE authorization-evidence
        profile <xref target="MUNOZ-WIMSE-EVIDENCE"/> describe adjacent
        runtime authorization and signed-evidence compositions. AEB treats
        their selected credentials, tokens, and evidence records as native
        inputs. It does not replace their issuance, verification, or
        authorization semantics.</t>
        <t>Headers, routing metadata, forwarded identity, trace context, or
        other values that an intermediary can add, remove, or mutate outside
        the validated end-to-end integrity coverage MUST NOT be load-bearing
        authorization evidence. They MAY be used for routing or diagnostics.
        If such a value affects the protected consequence, the boundary MUST
        derive it independently or require it to be covered by accepted native
        integrity and the observed action's material binding.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="per-action-native">
        <name>Attested Per-Action Tokens and Permit Records</name>
        <t>Attested per-action tokens, including artifacts described by a
        deployment as OASNT-like, remain native evidence formats. AEB does not
        assign that descriptive label a token type, claim set, registry entry,
        or trust meaning. The selected native verifier determines what the
        token proves and exposes its integrity-protected action commitment,
        issuer, audience, validity, freshness, status, and bounded result to
        the AEB adapter.</t>
        <t>SCITT Permit records defined by
        <xref target="MUNOZ-PERMIT"/> likewise remain native pre-execution
        decision evidence. AEB does not reserialize a Permit or convert it
        into an AEB receipt. It verifies the selected Permit revision through
        its native adapter, maps its protected material action only through a
        pinned CAID profile, and assigns it only to evidence roles permitted by
        the relying party's AEC requirement.</t>
        <t>A native format's valid signature proves only the statement and
        signer semantics that format defines. It does not, without an
        additional accepted profile and evidence, prove that a natural person
        operated the workload, understood the action, held authority, or
        performed a particular approval ceremony.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conformance">
      <name>Conformance and Deployment Claims</name>
      <t>An implementation conforms to AEB only if every protected invocation
      follows the ordered processing model in <xref target="processing"/> and
      fails closed on every missing or ambiguous required transition. A
      deployment MUST document:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>the protected action types and the effect paths actually mediated;</li>
        <li>the trusted configuration and durable-state boundaries;</li>
        <li>the native verifier revisions and relying-party pins;</li>
        <li>the method used to derive material action fields at the boundary;</li>
        <li>the consumption, reservation, and cross-replica fencing mechanism;</li>
        <li>the authoritative sources and matching rules used for
        reconciliation; and</li>
        <li>all direct, break-glass, administrator, alternate-protocol, and
        system-of-record paths that bypass the AEB implementation.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>An implementation placed beside a write path is not complete
      mediation. A deployment MUST NOT claim complete mediation unless the
      protected system rejects all material alternate paths or subjects them
      to an equivalent boundary. Observe-only operation MAY be useful during
      deployment, but it MUST NOT be described as enforcement.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>Cross-binding.</strong> An attacker can splice a valid permit,
      approval, credential, or receipt for action A into a request for action
      B. Native verification before mapping, executor-owned action
      construction, exact CAID matching, and a relying-party-pinned AEC
      requirement are all required defenses. Omitting any one of them reopens
      the attack.</t>
      <t><strong>Mutable context.</strong> Intermediary-added headers and agent
      annotations are convenient but are not trustworthy merely because they
      arrived on an authenticated hop. Every load-bearing field needs accepted
      end-to-end integrity coverage or independent derivation at the effect
      boundary.</t>
      <t><strong>Time of check and time of use.</strong> The action passed to
      the executor must be the frozen action that was verified, matched,
      satisfied, authorized, and consumed or reserved. Mutable aliases,
      provider defaults, exchange rates, destinations, branch heads, and
      policy epochs can change a consequence after approval; profiles must
      bind or revalidate them as material fields.</t>
      <t><strong>Replay and distributed state.</strong> Process-local caches are
      insufficient where replicas can invoke the same effect. Replay,
      consumption, reservation, and operation ownership state must be durable,
      atomic, and shared across every boundary instance that can reach the
      protected executor.</t>
      <t><strong>Freshness and revocation.</strong> Expiration, nonce checks,
      credential status, authority status, and policy epoch are separate
      checks. A fresh message does not make a revoked credential valid, and a
      current credential does not make old per-action evidence fresh.</t>
      <t><strong>Indeterminate effects.</strong> Retrying after a timeout can
      duplicate a payment, mutation, disclosure, or physical action. An
      invocation that might have reached the provider consumes the operation's
      retry right until authenticated reconciliation resolves the exact
      outcome. Caller assurances and unauthenticated webhooks do not resolve
      it.</t>
      <t><strong>Signature overclaiming.</strong> A cryptographic signature can
      establish control of a key and integrity of covered content under a
      selected verification profile. It does not inherently identify a human,
      prove human operation, prove comprehension, establish legal authority,
      or prove execution.</t>
      <t><strong>Boundary bypass.</strong> A correct AEB implementation does not
      protect direct database credentials, alternate APIs, shell access,
      administrator consoles, side channels, or actuator paths that bypass it.
      Deployment topology and credential placement are security properties,
      not implementation details.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>Action objects and evidence can expose identities, destinations,
      resources, policy choices, commercial relationships, and sensitive
      operational timing. Deployments SHOULD minimize the evidence passed to
      the executor and retained in portable records, use opaque high-entropy
      references where appropriate, and avoid treating a plain digest of
      low-entropy personal data as anonymization.</t>
      <t>Reconciliation queries can disclose that an operation is disputed or
      uncertain. They SHOULD be authenticated, authorized, rate-limited, and
      limited to the exact operation. AEB does not require public disclosure
      of native evidence or local policy.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relationship">
      <name>Relationship to EMILIA and Adjacent Work</name>
      <t>CAID <xref target="CAID"/> owns typed material-action identity and
      exact, relying-party-pinned cross-format mapping. AEB invokes CAID after
      native verification and does not extend CAID with trust semantics.</t>
      <t>AEC <xref target="AEC"/> owns heterogeneous evidence composition and
      the SATISFIED or UNSATISFIED result under a relying-party requirement.
      AEB invokes AEC and then makes the separate local authorization and
      effect-lifecycle decisions.</t>
      <t>Authorization Receipts <xref target="RECEIPTS"/> define one native
      action-bound organizational approval artifact and its receipt-specific
      consumption semantics. AEB does not make that format mandatory and does
      not generalize every native artifact into an EMILIA receipt.</t>
      <t>This document is intended to absorb the lifecycle responsibilities of
      draft-schrock-agent-action-manifest-00,
      draft-schrock-authorization-evidence-challenge-00, and
      draft-schrock-ep-enforcement-point-00. Static declaration, dynamic
      challenge, fail-closed enforcement, one-time consumption, invocation,
      and outcome handling are specified here as one boundary lifecycle.
      Their earlier wire shapes remain historical inputs; AEB conformance does
      not require a new common envelope for them.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. In particular, it creates no
      registry for native evidence types, lifecycle labels, verifier adapters,
      action mappings, or policy identifiers.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="CAID" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier/">
          <front>
            <title>The Canonical Action Identifier (CAID)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-canonical-action-identifier-00"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="AEC" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain/">
          <front>
            <title>Authorization Evidence Chains: Composing Heterogeneous Agent-Action Evidence (EP-AEC)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain-04"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9421.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="RECEIPTS" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
          <front>
            <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-08"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="WIMSE-HTTP" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-wimse-http-signature/">
          <front>
            <title>WIMSE Workload-to-Workload Authentication with HTTP Signatures</title>
            <author fullname="Joseph Salowey" initials="J." surname="Salowey"/>
            <author fullname="Yaron Sheffer" initials="Y." surname="Sheffer"/>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-wimse-http-signature-05"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MUNOZ-PERMIT" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-munoz-scitt-permit-profile/">
          <front>
            <title>A SCITT Profile for Pre-Execution AI Action Authorization Records</title>
            <author fullname="Christian Munoz" initials="C." surname="Munoz"/>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-munoz-scitt-permit-profile-01"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MUNOZ-WIMSE-EVIDENCE" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-munoz-wimse-authorization-evidence/">
          <front>
            <title>Signed Authorization-Evidence Records for WIMSE-Authorized AI Agent Actions</title>
            <author fullname="Christian Munoz" initials="C." surname="Munoz"/>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-munoz-wimse-authorization-evidence-01"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="KLRC-AUTH" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-klrc-aiagent-auth/">
          <front>
            <title>AI Agent Authentication and Authorization</title>
            <author fullname="Pieter Kasselman" initials="P." surname="Kasselman"/>
            <author fullname="Jeff Lombardo" initials="J." surname="Lombardo"/>
            <author fullname="Yaroslav Rosomakho" initials="Y." surname="Rosomakho"/>
            <author fullname="Brian Campbell" initials="B." surname="Campbell"/>
            <author fullname="Nick Steele" initials="N." surname="Steele"/>
            <author fullname="Aaron Parecki" initials="A." surname="Parecki"/>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-klrc-aiagent-auth-03"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgments">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>External review sharpened the boundaries between workload and message
      integrity, per-action authorization evidence, credential status, human
      operation, and executor-owned effect control. Those distinctions are
      load-bearing in this document. Acknowledgment does not imply endorsement.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
