<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-assurance-classes-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Authorization Assurance Classes">Assurance Classes for Authorization Receipts</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-assurance-classes-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="12"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>assurance</keyword>
    <keyword>receipts</keyword>
    <keyword>quorum</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Authorization of a high-risk agent action is not binary. A
      software signer asserting a policy decision, an authenticated human
      clicking approve, a human completing a device user-verification
      ceremony, and a quorum of distinct humans each doing so are four
      materially different levels of assurance — and a policy for a
      consequential action needs to say which level it demands.</t>
      <t>This document defines a small, ordered taxonomy of assurance
      classes for authorization receipts
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> — Class S,
      Class H, Class V, and Class Q — the monotonic comparison rule by
      which a required class is satisfied, and the central anti-forgery
      invariant that a class asserted in a receipt payload is treated as
      the lowest class until it is proof-backed. The taxonomy is the
      policy primitive an enforcement point, a manifest, or an authority
      registry uses to express and check "how strong must the human
      authorization be?"</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>A policy that says only "this action requires authorization"
      underspecifies the control. Releasing a $10 refund and wiring
      $10M do not warrant the same authorization strength, and a system
      that treats a software-signed decision and a two-person
      device-verified approval as equivalent has no defense in depth.
      What is missing is a shared, ordered vocabulary for
      <em>how strong</em> the human authorization behind a receipt is,
      so that policy can require a floor and a verifier can enforce it.</t>
      <t>This document defines that vocabulary as four assurance classes
      and the rule for comparing them. It does not define how a signature
      is produced, how a key is held, or how a quorum is gathered; those
      belong to the authorization-receipt specification
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> and to
      deployment. It defines only the classes, their order, the
      satisfaction rule, and the requirement that a claimed class be
      proven rather than trusted.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="classes">
      <name>The Assurance Classes</name>
      <t>Four assurance classes are defined, in increasing order of
      assurance. Three of the four map to a concrete assurance value
      string carried in a receipt; the member that carries the value is
      defined by the receipt profile in use, not by this document, which
      defines only the class identifiers, their order, and the value
      set. Class H is RESERVED and has no value assigned. The
      identifiers are mnemonic (S for
      software, H for authenticated human, V for device-verified human,
      Q for quorum) and are deliberately disjoint from the key-custody
      classes (Class A, Class B, Class C) of
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>, which
      classify who holds the approver's signing key, not how strong the
      authorization ceremony behind a receipt was.</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Class S — software / automation signer (receipt assurance value: "software")</dt>
        <dd>The authorization is asserted by a software component or
        automation key, not by a human completing an interactive
        ceremony. This is the lowest class and the default floor
        (<xref target="floor"/>). Appropriate for low-risk or read-mostly
        actions.</dd>
        <dt>Class H — authenticated human, no device user verification (RESERVED, OPTIONAL)</dt>
        <dd>A human authenticated to the approving system approved the
        action, but without a hardware user-verification ceremony bound
        to the signing key. Class H is defined for deployments that
        distinguish an authenticated-human approval from a device-verified
        one; a deployment that does not make this distinction need not
        implement Class H.</dd>
        <dt>Class V — device user-verified human (receipt assurance value: "class_a")</dt>
        <dd>A named human completed a device user-verification ceremony
        (for example WebAuthn user verification / passkey with a local
        gesture) whose result is bound to the signing key that produced
        the receipt. This is the baseline for high-risk actions. The
        receipt assurance value "class_a" is retained unchanged for
        compatibility with deployed receipts; it names the key-custody
        Class A ceremony of
        <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> that
        proves this assurance class, and is a value string, not an
        identifier of this taxonomy.</dd>
        <dt>Class Q — quorum of distinct humans (receipt assurance value: "quorum")</dt>
        <dd>Two or more distinct humans, each meeting at least Class V,
        authorized the same action under an m-of-n rule with distinct-human
        enforcement. Class Q is the highest class and the appropriate
        floor for critical, separation-of-duties actions.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="compare">
      <name>The Comparison Rule</name>
      <t>The classes form a total order:</t>
      <t><tt>Class S &lt; Class H &lt; Class V &lt; Class Q</tt></t>
      <t>A policy states the minimum class an action requires. A receipt
      satisfies the requirement if and only if its <em>proven</em> class
      (<xref target="floor"/>) is greater than or equal to the required
      class on this order. A verifier MUST reject a receipt whose proven
      class is lower than the required class, and MUST fail closed when
      it cannot determine the proven class.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="floor">
      <name>Proof-Backed Assurance (the Anti-Forgery Invariant)</name>
      <t>A class value present in a receipt payload is a <em>claim</em>,
      not evidence. An attacker who can shape a payload can write
      <tt>"quorum"</tt> into it as easily as <tt>"software"</tt>.
      Therefore:</t>
      <t>A verifier MUST treat a claimed assurance class as the lowest
      class (Class S) until the class is proof-backed by evidence the
      verifier independently checks — for example a device
      user-verification attestation for Class V, or the required number
      of distinct, individually verified human signatures for Class Q. A
      receipt that asserts Class V or Class Q without the corresponding
      proof MUST be treated as Class S for the comparison in
      <xref target="compare"/>.</t>
      <t>This inverts the trust default: assurance is earned by proof, not
      granted by assertion. It is the difference between a system that can
      be talked into a high-assurance decision and one that cannot.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Relationship to Other Profiles</name>
      <t>The assurance class is the shared policy primitive across the EP
      profiles: an Agent Action Manifest declares the class an action
      requires; an enforcement point compares the proven class of a
      presented receipt against that requirement; an authority registry
      records the maximum class a given approver is entitled to assert.
      This document defines the classes and their comparison; those
      profiles consume them.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>Downgrade and class-confusion.</strong> The comparison
      rule is only sound if the proven class cannot be inflated by a
      claim. The proof-backed invariant (<xref target="floor"/>) is the
      control; implementations MUST NOT read the class from an untrusted
      payload field and act on it without verifying the underlying
      evidence.</t>
      <t><strong>Fail closed on ambiguity.</strong> If a verifier cannot
      establish the proven class — missing attestation, unrecognized
      evidence, partial quorum — it MUST treat the receipt as failing the
      requirement, never as provisionally meeting it.</t>
      <t><strong>Quorum distinctness.</strong> Class Q depends on the
      distinctness of the humans in the quorum; a quorum satisfied by one
      human holding multiple keys, or by an initiator approving their own
      action, does not meet Class Q regardless of signature count.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. A future revision may request
      an IANA registry for authorization-receipt assurance classes; the
      four classes here are defined in-document pending that.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner"/>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author fullname="B. Leiba" initials="B." surname="Leiba"/>
          <date year="2017" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP)</title>
          <author fullname="I. Schrock" initials="I." surname="Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-06"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
