<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-authority-introduction-01"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Authority Introduction">Authority Documents and Scoped Authority for Agent-Action Evidence</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authority-introduction-01"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="14"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>trust establishment</keyword>
    <keyword>key rotation</keyword>
    <keyword>introduction</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Signature verification answers whether a key produced an
      artifact. It does not answer why a relying party accepts that key,
      or whether the key holder had authority for the action. This
      document specifies two composable artifacts. An Authority Document
      introduces and rotates an organization's evidence-issuing keys
      through a signed, hash-chained sequence. A Scoped Authority Proof
      records the authority held by a subject at a registry snapshot,
      including role, action scope, material limits, policy binding,
      validity, and revocation status. A relying party evaluates both
      artifacts under its own pinned trust inputs and policy. The design
      does not make a self-presented key authoritative, does not turn log
      inclusion or domain control into automatic trust, and does not
      equate a valid signature with permission to act.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document follows the distinction between VERIFIED and
      ACCEPTED. Verification establishes cryptographic and structural
      facts given a key. Acceptance is a relying-party decision about
      which keys, issuers, authority sources, and policies are
      admissible. Existing systems use certificates, federation
      metadata, trust bundles, transparency services, and deployment
      configuration for portions of that decision. Agent-action evidence
      profiles still need a concrete way to bind those trust inputs to
      the issuer key and to the human authority being relied upon.</t>
      <t>The design is deliberately not a universal public-key
      infrastructure. The relying party selects its trust anchors and
      acceptance policy. Domain control, log inclusion, and endorsement
      are evidence inputs, not authority by themselves. The goal is a
      reproducible answer to two narrower questions: which evidence key
      was valid at issuance, and what scoped authority did the approving
      subject hold for the exact action under review?</t>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
        all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="doc">
      <name>The Authority Document (EP-AUTHORITY-DOC-v1)</name>
      <t>An authority document is a JSON object, served from the
      organization's own origin (RECOMMENDED:
      /.well-known/ep-authority.json) and registrable to a transparency
      service:</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@version": "EP-AUTHORITY-DOC-v1",
  "org": { "name": "...", "domain": "acme.example" },
  "seq": 3,
  "prev_doc_digest": "sha256:<core digest of doc seq 2>",
  "root_key": "<b64url SPKI>",
  "issuer_keys": [
    { "kid": "<hex>", "key": "<b64url SPKI>",
      "usages": ["evidence_issuer", "authority_proof_issuer"],
      "valid_from": "...", "valid_to": "...",
      "revoked_at": "<OPTIONAL>" }
  ],
  "issued_at": "...",
  "sig": "<root_key over the canonical core>",
  "continuity_sig": "<by a key from the PREVIOUS doc>",
  "endorsements": [ { "by_org": "...", "by_key": "...",
                      "doc_digest": "...", "sig": "..." } ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The signed core is the document without sig, continuity_sig,
      and endorsements; its canonical digest is the document's identity.
      Endorsements are countersignatures over that digest by OTHER
      authorities — third-party attestations that ride with the
      document without being part of it.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="scoped-authority">
      <name>Scoped Authority Proof (EP-AUTHORITY-PROOF-v1)</name>
      <t>An accepted issuer key with the authority_proof_issuer usage MAY
      sign a snapshot of one subject's authority. The proof records what
      the authority source asserted at issuance; it does not grant
      authority merely because it is carried with an action.</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@type": "EP-AUTHORITY-PROOF-v1",
  "authority_id": "auth_cfo",
  "subject": "ep:approver:ada",
  "organization_id": "org1",
  "role": "cfo",
  "scope": ["payment.release"],
  "limits": { "max_amount_usd": 50000, "currency": "USD" },
  "validity": {
    "from": "2026-01-01T00:00:00Z",
    "to": "2027-01-01T00:00:00Z"
  },
  "revocation": {
    "status": "not_revoked",
    "checked_at": "2026-07-14T16:00:00Z"
  },
  "registry_head": "sha256:<snapshot digest>",
  "registry_epoch": 17,
  "policy_hash": "sha256:<applicable policy digest>",
  "issued_at": "2026-07-14T16:00:00Z",
  "signature": {
    "algorithm": "Ed25519",
    "key_id": "ep:authority-registry-key:sha256:<prefix>",
    "public_key": "<b64url SPKI>",
    "proof_digest": "sha256:<signed-body digest>",
    "signature_b64u": "<signature>"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The signed body is the proof without the signature member,
      domain-separated with the ASCII string "EP-AUTHORITY-PROOF-v1"
      followed by a zero octet, and canonicalized using JCS
      <xref target="RFC8785"/>. The public key carried in the signature
      envelope is a verification input only. It MUST NOT establish its
      own authority. A relying party MUST resolve it through an accepted
      Authority Document or match it to an independently pinned authority
      issuer key.</t>
      <t>The max_amount_usd field is the implemented v1 monetary limit.
      It permits no currency conversion: a proof denominated in USD MUST
      NOT satisfy a limit check for another currency. Profiles that need
      other monetary representations MUST define their canonical amount
      and comparison rules rather than relying on floating-point currency
      conversion.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authority-evaluation">
      <name>Authority Evaluation</name>
      <t>Given an action, its authorization evidence, an Authority Proof,
      and relying-party trust inputs, a verifier MUST perform all of the
      following checks. A missing or failed required check produces a
      refusal; no unknown value is treated as permission.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Verify the proof digest and signature and establish that the
        signing key is accepted for authority-proof issuance.</li>
        <li>Match subject and organization to the approving identity and
        action context. A proof for one subject or organization MUST NOT
        be substituted for another.</li>
        <li>Require the action type to be within scope and any required
        role to match.</li>
        <li>Apply every material limit. If a capped action omits the
        amount or currency needed for comparison, refuse it.</li>
        <li>Check that the action authorization time falls within the
        authority validity window and that the policy hash, when present,
        matches the policy being evaluated.</li>
        <li>Check the registry head and minimum epoch required by the
        relying party. A stale or unavailable required authority view is
        not equivalent to an unbounded grant.</li>
        <li>Apply revocation at its effective time. Terminal revocation
        evidence does not age out. A not_revoked snapshot establishes
        only the status observed at checked_at; current status is a
        separate, freshness-bounded input
        <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-revocation-statement"/>.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>Portable profiles SHOULD express ceremony strength as
      verifier-visible proof predicates, such as user verification,
      named-human binding, or device binding. This document does not
      define a universal letter-grade assurance taxonomy.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="separation-of-duties">
      <name>Separation of Duties and Quorum</name>
      <t>Authority and independence are different properties. An
      authority source can establish that a subject is eligible to
      approve an action; it cannot establish that the subject did not
      initiate that same action merely by asserting a flag. Initiator
      exclusion MUST be evaluated by joining the signed initiator and
      approver identities for the action. For a quorum, every counted
      approver MUST have its own accepted authority proof, and the
      authorization profile MUST separately enforce distinct-human and
      initiator-exclusion requirements.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="continuity">
      <name>Rotation, Continuity, and Time-of-Issuance</name>
      <t>Documents chain: seq increments by one, prev_doc_digest names
      the previous core digest, and each rotation MUST carry a
      continuity signature by the previous document's root key or one
      of its non-revoked issuer keys. A verifier walking the chain
      therefore needs exactly one leap — the first document it ever
      saw — and every subsequent rotation is mechanically checkable. A
      rotation without valid continuity MUST be flagged, never silently
      accepted; whether endorsements can substitute for continuity is
      the relying party's policy (<xref target="compromise"/>), not a
      default.</t>
      <t>Two invariants govern key resolution, and implementations
      that miss either will hurt someone:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Time of issuance. An artifact verifies against the key that
        was valid WHEN THE ARTIFACT WAS ISSUED. Rotation never
        invalidates previously issued evidence, and a revocation voids
        a key only for signatures claimed at or after revoked_at —
        honest history survives compromise.</li>
        <li>Newest document authoritative. The newest document that
        mentions a key identifier is authoritative for it. A
        revocation recorded in document N MUST NOT be undone by
        resolving the same key identifier against the pre-revocation
        entry in document N-1.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section anchor="equivocation">
      <name>Anti-Equivocation</name>
      <t>A malicious authority might show different documents to
      different relying parties. The hash chain exposes a fork when a
      verifier possesses both branches or a previously pinned head.
      Registration to a transparency service <xref target="RFC9943"/>
      can make revisions discoverable, but inclusion in one log view
      alone does not prove global consistency. Split-view resistance
      requires an independently checked consistency mechanism such as
      witnesses, gossip, or cross-logging. A profile MUST state which
      of those observations it requires; this document does not convert
      log inclusion into automatic acceptance.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="graded">
      <name>Introduction as Evidence: Graded, Replayable Acceptance</name>
      <t>Acceptance is not a boolean in a config file; it is a verdict
      over introduction evidence, evaluated under a RELYING-PARTY
      policy, using the same closed-verdict classification and
      replay-digest discipline as the evidence-sufficiency layer this
      family defines for actions
      (<xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/>). The
      evidence facts: the authority chain itself (consistent, signed,
      no unexplained continuity breaks); domain binding (the relying
      party's own attested observation that it fetched this document
      digest from the organization's origin); transparency-log
      inclusion and FIRST-LOGGED AGE (history can be a policy input,
      particularly when the history is independently witnessed); and endorsements,
      graded by whether the endorser is among the relying party's own
      pinned anchors.</t>
      <t>Policies are per action class. A relying party can require
      stronger introduction evidence for money movement than for a
      low-impact action. New observations, such as an endorsement from
      an already pinned anchor or a longer witnessed history, may satisfy
      an unchanged policy, but they never alter that policy and never
      compel acceptance. The replay result MUST identify the policy and
      observations used so another evaluator can reproduce the decision.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="compromise">
      <name>Compromise Recovery</name>
      <t>If an authority loses its keys entirely, continuity breaks by
      construction. The recovery path is explicit rather than
      exceptional: the successor document is published with no (or
      invalid) continuity signature, the break is flagged by every
      verifier, and the relying party's policy decides what
      substitutes — typically an endorsement threshold (a quorum of
      the relying party's pinned anchors countersigning the successor
      document) plus a revocation statement over the compromised keys.
      A relying party with no such policy simply continues to refuse:
      fail closed is the default, recovery is opt-in.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Nothing creates trust from nothing, and this document does
      not claim to. It makes the bootstrap and scoped-authority inputs
      explicit and permits their checks to be replayed. The residual
      assumptions are named:
      domain binding inherits the Web PKI and is worth exactly that;
      log-backed consistency is as strong as the log's operator or the
      cross-log witnessing above it; endorsements are as strong as the
      endorser and mean nothing until a relying party pins one.
      A presenter-supplied key cannot establish its own authority.
      Key-resurrection (resolving a revoked key through an older
      document) is defeated by the newest-document-authoritative rule.
      Hash chaining detects conflicting branches only when the verifier
      has a comparison point; a single log view is insufficient to prove
      non-equivocation. Rotation-based history rewriting is constrained
      by time-of-issuance resolution. No combination of missing
      observations grades toward acceptance.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. A well-known URI
      registration (ep-authority.json) is anticipated for a future
      revision.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9943.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph/">
          <front>
            <title>Action Evidence Graphs and Evidence Policy Replay for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-AEG)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-revocation-statement" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-revocation-statement/">
          <front>
            <title>Revocation Statements for Agent-Action Authorization Evidence</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-revocation-statement-00"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="impl">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>Two Apache-2.0 reference components are published in the
      EMILIA Protocol repository. lib/authority/authority-doc.js covers
      document creation, rotation, chain verification, time-of-issuance
      key resolution, endorsement verification, and introduction-policy
      replay. lib/authority/proof.js and lib/authority/resolver.js cover
      signed scoped-authority proofs and closed authority verdicts. The
      authority vector suite contains 27 cases, including unpinned-key,
      issuer-substitution, amount, currency, scope, role, lifecycle,
      policy, delegation, malformed-time, registry-head, and stale-epoch
      refusals. This revision does not claim an integrated conformance
      result for resolving an Authority Proof key through an Authority
      Document; that join and its cross-language vectors are required
      before publication of this revision.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
