<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-scitt-authorization-evidence-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Human-Authorization Evidence">A Human-Authorization Evidence Profile for SCITT Agent-Action Statements</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-scitt-authorization-evidence-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="2"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>SCITT</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>receipts</keyword>
    <keyword>transparency</keyword>
    <keyword>human oversight</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>A growing family of drafts records what an autonomous agent did:
      per-action receipt envelopes, action capsules, post-execution
      evidence profiles, pre-execution permits, and refusal events, all
      composing on the SCITT transparency architecture
      <xref target="RFC9943"/>. These profiles establish that an action
      was logged, that a workload or token acted, and that policy
      allowed it. None of them emits the artifact that regulated and
      high-consequence deployments require: portable, offline-verifiable
      evidence that a named, accountable human (or a quorum of humans)
      authorized this exact irreversible action before it executed.</t>
      <t>This document defines a small, reusable
      <em>authorization-evidence</em> profile: how a SCITT-family
      agent-action statement references a named-human authorization
      receipt by digest, and how a relying party verifies that the
      referenced authorization and the recorded action are about the
      same operation. The referenced receipt is an EMILIA Protocol (EP)
      authorization receipt
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>, verifiable
      fully offline and independent of the operator, the agent runtime,
      and the transparency service. The profile composes by shared
      digest, not by containment: a host statement commits to the
      authorization without restating it.</t>
      <t>This profile is complementary to, not a replacement for, the
      SCITT architecture and the agent-action, permit, and identity work
      that composes with it. It defines no transparency log, no action
      envelope, no policy language, and no agent-identity scheme; it
      defines only the reference and verification of the human-authorization
      leg those layers assume but do not themselves produce.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Autonomous agents increasingly hold credentials sufficient to
      perform irreversible operations: releasing payments, changing
      beneficiary records, rotating production credentials, deleting
      data. A rapidly growing set of specifications makes those actions
      observable and accountable. The SCITT architecture
      <xref target="RFC9943"/> provides append-only transparency and
      inclusion proofs for signed statements. Agent-action work layered
      on it records per-action receipts, action capsules, and
      post-execution evidence; pre-execution permit profiles express
      allow/deny/challenge decisions; refusal-event work records safety
      declinations; workload-identity and transaction-token work assert
      which principal acted.</t>
      <t>Each of these answers a different question, and none answers the
      one that matters at the moment an irreversible action executes:
      <em>which accountable human authorized this exact action, and can a
      third party verify that without trusting the operator?</em> The
      emerging gap is therefore not a shortage of agent logs or action
      envelopes. It is the absence of a portable human-authorization
      artifact that can be verified independently of the operator, the
      agent runtime, and the transparency service — and that any of the
      above profiles can reference.</t>
      <t>This document defines that reference. It specifies how an
      agent-action statement carries an <em>authorization-evidence
      reference</em> to a named-human (or quorum) authorization receipt,
      and the verification procedure a relying party runs to confirm
      that the recorded action and the referenced authorization bind the
      same operation. The referenced receipt is an EP authorization
      receipt <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>: an
      approver holding their own key signs a canonical Authorization
      Context over the exact action, the authorization is consumed
      exactly once, and the resulting receipt verifies offline. This
      profile does not redefine that receipt; it defines only how a host
      statement points at one and how the linkage is checked.</t>
      <t>The design principle throughout is <em>composition by digest,
      not containment</em>. A host statement never restates the human
      approval; it commits to the exact bytes of the authorization by
      digest, so the two artifacts remain independently verifiable and
      the human-authorization evidence is neither duplicated nor
      weakened.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Action</dt>
        <dd>The exact irreversible operation under consideration,
        expressed as a canonical value (for example, an action type, a
        target, and material parameters).</dd>
        <dt>Host statement</dt>
        <dd>A SCITT-family agent-action statement: a per-action
        receipt, action capsule, permit, or post-execution evidence
        record — that records or authorizes an Action and that carries
        an authorization-evidence reference under this profile.</dd>
        <dt>Authorization receipt</dt>
        <dd>An EP authorization receipt
        <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>: an
        offline-verifiable artifact in which a named human or a quorum
        signs over the exact Action before execution.</dd>
        <dt>Subject digest</dt>
        <dd><tt>SHA-256(JCS(Action))</tt> — the digest of the canonical
        JSON <xref target="RFC8785"/> encoding of the Action. Both the
        host statement and the authorization receipt are ABOUT the same
        Action when they yield the same subject digest.</dd>
        <dt>Authority-reference digest</dt>
        <dd>The digest a host statement embeds to commit to the
        authorization receipt (see <xref target="reference"/>).</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rule">
      <name>Composition Rule</name>
      <t>A conforming host statement MUST compose with an authorization
      receipt by reference, not by containment. Specifically:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>The host statement MUST commit to the Action by a subject
        digest computed as <tt>SHA-256(JCS(Action))</tt>. It MUST NOT
        rely on a self-asserted subject digest supplied by the party
        being held accountable; a verifier MUST be able to recompute the
        subject digest from the Action itself.</li>
        <li>The host statement MUST carry exactly one authority-reference
        digest committing to the authorization receipt for that Action
        (<xref target="reference"/>).</li>
        <li>The host statement MUST NOT restate the human approval
        (approver identity, signature, or decision) as its own trusted
        assertion. Those live in the authorization receipt and are
        verified there.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>This keeps the two artifacts independently verifiable: a relying
      party can check the recorded action against one and the human
      authorization against the other, and confirm they concern the same
      operation, without either artifact having to trust the other's
      issuer.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="reference">
      <name>The Authorization-Evidence Reference</name>
      <t>The authority-reference digest is one of the following,
      selected per deployment and fixed for a given host-statement
      profile so that both implementations bind identical bytes:</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>receipt_payload_digest</dt>
        <dd><tt>SHA-256(JCS(receipt.payload))</tt> — used for offline
        composition, where the relying party holds or can fetch the EP
        receipt directly.</dd>
        <dt>statement_digest</dt>
        <dd><tt>SHA-256(COSE_Sign1 bytes)</tt> of the EP receipt
        expressed as a SCITT Signed Statement — RECOMMENDED when the
        receipt is registered in a transparency service, so the
        reference also resolves to a logged, inclusion-proofed entry.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The encoding of the EP receipt as a COSE_Sign1
      <xref target="RFC9052"/> Signed Statement, including the canonical
      payload and content type, is specified by the EP SCITT profile and
      is out of scope here; this document specifies only the digest that
      a host statement embeds and the verification that binds it.</t>
      <t>A host-statement profile adopting this document defines the
      concrete carrier for the authority-reference digest within its own
      structure (for example, a dedicated field in a per-action receipt,
      the opaque authority reference of an action capsule, or a
      <tt>human_authorization_evidence</tt> element of a permit). This
      document does not mandate a single carrier; it mandates the digest
      semantics and verification below.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verify">
      <name>Verification Procedure</name>
      <t>A relying party presented with a host statement and its
      referenced authorization receipt determines that the host
      statement is <em>authorization-backed</em> if and only if all of
      the following hold:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>The verifier recomputes the subject digest from the Action
        as <tt>SHA-256(JCS(Action))</tt> and confirms it matches the
        subject digest committed by the host statement.</li>
        <li>The verifier resolves the authority-reference digest to an EP
        authorization receipt (held locally, fetched offline, or
        retrieved from the transparency service when a
        <tt>statement_digest</tt> is used) and confirms the resolved
        receipt hashes to that digest.</li>
        <li>The authorization receipt itself verifies under
        <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>: a valid
        signature by an authorized approver (or a satisfied quorum) over
        the canonical Authorization Context, within its validity window,
        and not already consumed or refused.</li>
        <li>The Action the authorization receipt is over yields the same
        subject digest as step 1 — that is, the human authorized the
        exact operation the host statement records, not a different or
        broader one.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>If any step fails, the host statement MUST NOT be treated as
      authorization-backed. A verifier that cannot resolve or verify the
      referenced authorization MUST fail closed: absence of verifiable
      human authorization is not authorization.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verdict">
      <name>Verdict-Completeness</name>
      <t>Authorization evidence distinguishes three states, and only
      two of them are evidence. A DENIAL (an accountable human refused,
      an approval was revoked, or a validity window lapsed and the
      expiry was recorded) is a signed EP event; a host statement MAY
      reference a denied authorization exactly as it references an
      approval, so that "an accountable human refused this action" is a
      positive, verifiable fact. ABSENCE, by contrast, is not evidence
      and cannot be made so by assertion: the mere failure to present an
      authorization proves nothing to anyone. Absence becomes positive
      evidence only when a verifier or policy engine signs an
      OBSERVED-ABSENCE statement -- an attestation that it performed a
      defined lookup against defined sources at a stated time and found
      no qualifying authorization. Such a statement attests the search
      and its emptiness, not a universal negative. Verifiers MUST
      otherwise treat absence as an inference from silence: fail closed,
      but do not record it as a fact. Auditors and counterparties rely
      on refusals as much as approvals; this profile makes both --
      and honest observed-absence -- first-class.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Relationship to Adjacent Work</name>
      <t>This profile is deliberately narrow and composes with, rather
      than replaces, each adjacent layer:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>The SCITT architecture <xref target="RFC9943"/> provides
        transparency and inclusion; an EP receipt registered as a Signed
        Statement gains a logged, inclusion-proofed home, and its
        <tt>statement_digest</tt> becomes a resolvable authority
        reference. SCITT is agnostic about who authorized a statement;
        this profile supplies exactly that.</li>
        <li>Pre-execution permit work expresses allow/deny/challenge
        decisions; an EP receipt is the human-authorization evidence a
        permit carries when its policy demands an accountable human.</li>
        <li>Per-action receipt and action-capsule work records what an
        agent did; those envelopes carry the EP receipt as a
        human-authorization sub-reference by digest.</li>
        <li>Post-execution evidence and refusal-event work sits after or
        beside execution; an EP authorization is the pre-execution leg it
        links back to.</li>
        <li>Workload-identity and transaction-token work asserts which
        principal acted; the EP authority-reference digest can be bound
        into those flows to tie the workload's action to a named human's
        approval.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>In every case the composition is by digest, and the EP receipt
      answers only the human-authorization question. This profile makes
      no claim of a human in the real-time execution path: the authorization
      is pre-execution, may be delegated within bounds, and is evidenced
      after the fact by an offline-verifiable receipt.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t><strong>Recompute, never trust, the subject digest.</strong> A
      verifier MUST recompute the subject digest from the Action and MUST
      NOT accept a subject digest asserted by the host statement's
      issuer. Accepting a self-asserted digest would let a party bind a
      genuine human authorization for one action to a different recorded
      action.</t>
      <t><strong>Trust anchor is the approver's key, not the
      operator.</strong> The security of the human-authorization leg
      derives entirely from the EP receipt's signature by a key held by
      the accountable human or quorum, verified under
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>. The host
      statement's issuer, the agent runtime, and the transparency service
      are untrusted for this leg.</t>
      <t><strong>Fail closed.</strong> A relying party that cannot
      resolve the authority reference, cannot verify the EP receipt, or
      finds the receipt consumed, expired, or over a different action
      MUST NOT treat the host statement as authorization-backed.</t>
      <t><strong>Digest agility and second-preimage.</strong> This
      document specifies SHA-256 over RFC 8785 canonical JSON for both
      the subject digest and <tt>receipt_payload_digest</tt>.
      Deployments MUST use a collision- and second-preimage-resistant
      hash and MUST pin one canonicalization so that independent
      implementations bind identical bytes. Hash agility follows the
      referenced receipt and COSE specifications.</t>
      <t><strong>Replay.</strong> One-time consumption of the
      authorization is enforced by the EP receipt, not by this profile.
      A host statement that references a receipt does not itself re-open
      a replay window, but a verifier relying on <tt>allow</tt> semantics
      MUST honor the referenced receipt's consumption state.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. A future revision may request
      registration of a claim or COSE header parameter carrying the
      authority-reference digest; no such registration is requested at
      this time.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner"/>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author fullname="B. Leiba" initials="B." surname="Leiba"/>
          <date year="2017" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8785" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8785">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Canonicalization Scheme (JCS)</title>
          <author fullname="A. Rundgren" initials="A." surname="Rundgren"/>
          <author fullname="B. Jordan" initials="B." surname="Jordan"/>
          <author fullname="S. Erdtman" initials="S." surname="Erdtman"/>
          <date year="2020" month="June"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8785"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9052" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9052">
        <front>
          <title>CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE): Structures and Process</title>
          <author fullname="J. Schaad" initials="J." surname="Schaad"/>
          <date year="2022" month="August"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="96"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9052"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9943" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9943">
        <front>
          <title>An Architecture for Trustworthy and Transparent Digital Supply Chains</title>
          <author fullname="H. Birkholz" initials="H." surname="Birkholz"/>
          <author fullname="A. Delignat-Lavaud" initials="A." surname="Delignat-Lavaud"/>
          <author fullname="C. Fournet" initials="C." surname="Fournet"/>
          <author fullname="Y. Deshpande" initials="Y." surname="Deshpande"/>
          <author fullname="S. Lasker" initials="S." surname="Lasker"/>
          <date year="2026" month="June"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9943"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts">
        <front>
          <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP)</title>
          <author fullname="I. Schrock" initials="I." surname="Schrock"/>
          <date year="2026" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-05"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
