<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-human-oversight-profile-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EP Human-Oversight Profile">EMILIA Protocol: Human-Oversight Profile for Autonomous and High-Risk AI Systems</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-human-oversight-profile-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address><postal><country>US</country></postal><email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email></address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="June" day="28"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <keyword>human oversight</keyword>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>autonomy</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Governing instruments for high-risk and autonomous AI require a human to
      remain meaningfully in control of consequential actions, but none specifies
      an artifact that proves it, after the fact, to a third party, without
      trusting the operator. This document profiles the EMILIA Protocol (EP)
      authorization receipt (<xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>)
      as that verifiable human-oversight evidence layer. It defines how to apply
      the receipt primitive at authorization boundaries for both human-in-the-loop
      and human-on-the-loop control, a small set of OPTIONAL authorization-context
      conventions, and the relying-party rules that make "a human was meaningfully
      in control" a verifiable artifact rather than an operator-owned log entry.
      It introduces no new cryptography. The profile is scoped to evidence, not
      cognition: it proves the fact, scope, currency, and authority of human
      authorization; it does not prove the human understood, or that the decision
      was wise or lawful. It is a necessary, not sufficient, condition, and says so
      throughout. Primary applicability is civilian high-risk AI; defense and
      lethal-autonomy regimes are noted as further, secondary applicabilities.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro"><name>Introduction and Motivation</name>
      <t>Every governing instrument for high-risk and autonomous AI requires a
      human to remain meaningfully in control, yet none specifies an artifact that
      proves it to a third party without trusting the system operator. The lead
      applicabilities for this profile are civilian:</t>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>EU AI Act Article 14</strong> requires high-risk AI to be
        effectively overseen by natural persons who can interpret output, decline
        to act on it, and intervene or halt. (The AI Act, Art. 2(3), excludes
        systems used exclusively for military, defense, or national-security
        purposes; treat Art. 14 as a <em>civilian</em> applicability.)</li>
        <li><strong>NIST AI Risk Management Framework</strong> calls for
        documented, auditable human oversight.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The same evidence gap recurs in further, secondary applicabilities --
      DoD Directive 3000.09's "appropriate levels of human judgment over the use of
      force," and the UN CCW debate on meaningful human control of lethal
      autonomous systems -- which are noted here only to show the profile's reach,
      not as its primary framing. Across all of them the unsolved problem is the
      same: when an autonomous system acts, the record that a named human
      authorized that exact action -- at the right scope, currently, under the
      right authority -- is a log the operator controls and could forge, backfill,
      or rubber-stamp. EP closes that gap; this profile makes the mapping explicit.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="modes"><name>Control Modes and the Authorization Boundary</name>
      <t>This profile does NOT require per-machine-cycle human approval
      (incompatible with machine tempo). EP receipts are issued at <em>authorization
      boundaries</em> -- the discrete points where a human grants, scopes, or renews
      autonomous authority:</t>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>in_the_loop</strong> -- a human authorizes each discrete
        consequential action before it executes (one receipt per action; the system
        fails closed without it).</li>
        <li><strong>on_the_loop</strong> -- a human authorizes a bounded engagement
        envelope (action class, target/effect set, geofence, time window) within
        which the system may act autonomously, retaining a revocation/halt
        authority. One receipt authorizes the envelope; autonomy operates only
        inside it and only while unrevoked and unexpired.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="context"><name>Authorization-Context Conventions</name>
      <t>For the autonomy domain the receipt's authorization context
      <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> carry: <tt>control_mode</tt> (in_the_loop | on_the_loop);
      and an <tt>authorization_scope</tt> with <tt>effect_class</tt>,
      <tt>target_set</tt>, <tt>geofence</tt>, and <tt>window</tt>
      {<tt>not_before</tt>, <tt>not_after</tt>}. These are bounds the relying party
      enforces; they do not expand the core receipt's guarantees.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="pep"><name>Relying-Party (Enforcement) Rules</name>
      <t>A relying party (Policy Enforcement Point) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> act only on
      a valid receipt and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> fail closed otherwise. For
      on_the_loop, each individual action <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be checked against the
      authorized envelope (effect class, target set, geofence, window) offline; an
      out-of-envelope, expired, or revoked action <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be refused.
      Continuous evaluation and revocation apply (the halt authority). Higher
      assurance regimes (for example a two-person rule) <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use
      EP-QUORUM (m-of-n distinct humans). Where an action executes, the enforcement
      point <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> emit a post-execution receipt bound to the
      authorization (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-enforcement-point</tt>).</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="bound"><name>What It Proves, and What It Does Not</name>
      <t>The profile proves the fact, scope, currency, and authority of a named
      human's (or quorum's) authorization of an exact action or bounded envelope,
      offline-verifiable without trusting the operator. It does not
      prove that the human understood the action, was uncoerced, or that the action
      was lawful, wise, or proportional. Display-fidelity is a client-conformance
      concern; comprehension and lawfulness are out of band. Meaningful human
      control is necessary, not sufficient, and EP supplies the necessary,
      verifiable part.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security"><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Over-trust is the dominant risk: treating the existence of a receipt as
      proof an autonomous action was legitimate. A receipt proves authorization at
      a stated scope, currency, and authority -- nothing more. Coercion of an
      authorized human and authorization without comprehension are out of scope of
      the cryptographic guarantees; device-bound user verification and
      display-fidelity requirements raise but do not eliminate them. Per-component
      considerations are normative in the referenced documents.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document registers the <tt>control_mode</tt> values
      (in_the_loop, on_the_loop) in the EP profile registry. It has no other IANA
      actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references><name>References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts.xml"/>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
