<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-architecture-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EP Architecture">The EMILIA Protocol Architecture: A Human-Authorization and Oversight Evidence Layer for Agentic and Autonomous Systems</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-architecture-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="June" day="28"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <keyword>authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>human oversight</keyword>
    <keyword>accountability</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Autonomous and agentic systems now take consequential, often
      irreversible actions -- moving money, changing records, routing
      benefits, releasing effects -- at machine speed, while the evidence
      systems that establish accountability were built for the speed of
      humans taking those actions. Across regulation, audit, and insurance
      the same requirement recurs and the same artifact is missing: portable,
      offline-verifiable proof that a named, accountable human authorized a
      specific action before it executed, checkable by a third party without
      trusting the operator that produced it.</t>
      <t>This document is the architectural overview of the EMILIA Protocol
      (EP): a human-authorization and oversight evidence layer for agentic and
      autonomous systems. It defines the layer's position relative to agent
      identity, delegation, policy, and transparency work; states the design
      invariants; and ties together the component specifications -- the
      authorization receipt, multi-party quorum, the enforcement point, the
      authorization evidence chain, long-term evidence-record renewal, identity
      binding, and the human-oversight profile. EP composes with the other
      layers rather than replacing them; its contribution is the human-
      accountability apex and the composition seam that binds the layers'
      artifacts into one verifiable record.</t>
      <t>EP proves authorization -- that a named human (or quorum) approved the
      exact action. It does not prove the action was understood, lawful, wise,
      or proportional. It is a necessary, not sufficient, condition for
      accountable autonomy, and this document is explicit about that
      boundary.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Fifty years of access control answered "who is allowed in?" The
      dominant actors in software are no longer humans but agents that act on
      their behalf, and the unanswered question is no longer authentication but
      authorization at the moment of action: who approved that exact action,
      before it executed, and can anyone prove it later without trusting the
      system that produced the record?</t>
      <t>Today that proof is an operator-controlled log: forgeable,
      backfillable, and unverifiable by an outside party. Every governing
      instrument -- the EU AI Act's logging and human-oversight articles, the
      NIST AI Risk Management Framework, US sectoral controls requiring
      authorization and separation of duties, cyber and crime insurance
      conditions precedent, and, for defense autonomy, DoD Directive 3000.09's
      "appropriate levels of human judgment" -- requires verifiable human
      authorization and specifies no format for it. EP supplies the format.</t>
      <t>The architectural thesis is one sentence: no irreversible autonomous
      action without a verifiable human receipt.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="position">
      <name>Position in the Agent Stack</name>
      <t>EP is deliberately narrow in mechanism and broad in reach: it occupies
      the human-authorization layer and composes downward. Adjacent layers, and
      the relationship EP takes to each:</t>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Identity -- who the agent is.</strong> Workload and
        agent-identity efforts (WIMSE/SPIFFE,
        <xref target="I-D.klrc-aiagent-auth"/>) authenticate the agent. EP does
        not re-solve this; it references the identity evidence a decision relied
        on (<xref target="components"/>) and authorizes the action above it.</li>
        <li><strong>Delegation -- the agent is authorized to act for a
        principal.</strong> <xref target="I-D.nelson-agent-delegation-receipts"/>
        (DRP), OAuth token-exchange / identity-chaining, and agent-grant profiles
        establish delegated authority. EP composes with these by reference; it
        does not duplicate them.</li>
        <li><strong>Policy / permit -- machine policy allows the effect.</strong>
        Policy-decision and route/permit efforts decide whether an effect is
        allowed. EP's enforcement point consumes such a decision and records the
        human authorization that backed it; EP is not the policy engine.</li>
        <li><strong>Transparency -- append-only logging.</strong> Transparency
        substrates (SCITT, COSE Receipts, CT-style logs) provide tamper-evident
        records. EP can anchor to them, but its receipts are self-contained and
        verifiable offline without a mandatory external log.</li>
        <li><strong>Human authorization and oversight -- a named, accountable
        human approved this exact action.</strong> This layer is thin and largely
        unfilled. It is EP's.</li>
      </ul>
      <t><strong>L4 to L7 binding.</strong> Because a human authorization is only
      as trustworthy as the upstream identity/delegation evidence it relied on,
      EP records that evidence inside the signed authorization context and can
      enforce its freshness fail-closed. This keeps EP agnostic to which identity
      or delegation standard prevails while making a stale or unconstrained
      upstream claim detectable after the fact.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="components">
      <name>Components</name>
      <t>EP is a small family of specifications around one primitive. Each makes
      a distinct, independently verifiable claim; together they form the
      human-authorization and oversight evidence layer. Component specifications
      are published as separate EMILIA Protocol Internet-Drafts
      (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-*</tt>).</t>
      <section anchor="c-receipt"><name>Authorization Receipt -- the core primitive</name>
        <t>A named human's device-bound signoff over one exact, canonicalized
        action (JCS, <xref target="RFC8785"/>; Ed25519), producing a Trust
        Receipt that a third party verifies fully offline. The apex of the
        layer. (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-quorum"><name>Quorum -- multi-party human authorization</name>
        <t>M-of-N approval by distinct humans with ordering and separation of
        duties -- the cryptographic form of the two-person rule, which a single
        compromised or coerced approver cannot satisfy alone.
        (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-quorum</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-pep"><name>Enforcement Point -- the Receipt-Required rail</name>
        <t>The fail-closed gate: a high-risk action is refused (HTTP 428-style)
        unless a valid, in-scope, unrevoked authorization receipt is present.
        "No receipt, no execution," expressed as a manifest-driven policy
        enforcement point.
        (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-enforcement-point</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-aec"><name>Authorization Evidence Chain -- the composition seam</name>
        <t>A standard for binding the artifacts of the adjacent layers -- an
        identity attestation, a delegation receipt, a policy decision, a
        transparency inclusion proof, and the EP human authorization -- into a
        single, order-preserving, verifiable evidence record. This is the
        connective tissue that lets independently produced proofs be checked as
        one chain.
        (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-authorization-evidence-chain</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-er"><name>Evidence Record -- long-term, crypto-agile preservation</name>
        <t>An Evidence Record Syntax-style (<xref target="RFC4998"/>) renewal
        chain so a receipt verifiable today remains verifiable after its original
        algorithms weaken (for example sha256 to sha384), meeting the multi-year
        retention schedules that regulation imposes on the records EP produces.
        (<tt>draft-schrock-ep-evidence-record</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-eye"><name>Identity Binding -- the named human, not a raw key</name>
        <t>A profile binding a signing key to a real, named, accountable person
        (and, where required, a device-bound, user-verified authenticator),
        closing the gap left by peers that bind only to an opaque public key.
        (<tt>draft-schrock-emilia-eye</tt>.)</t></section>
      <section anchor="c-oversight"><name>Human-Oversight Profile -- oversight of autonomous action</name>
        <t>An applicability profile for human-in-the-loop and human-on-the-loop
        oversight of autonomous and cyber-physical systems, mapping the components
        above to the human-oversight requirements of the NIST AI Risk Management
        Framework and, for civilian high-risk systems, EU AI Act Article 14, with
        DoD Directive 3000.09 as a further applicability. It introduces no new
        cryptography; it applies the receipt primitive at authorization
        boundaries. (Work in progress.)</t></section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="related">
      <name>Relationship to Other Work</name>
      <t>A per-component treatment appears in each component document; see in
      particular the Relationship to Other Work section of
      <tt>draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts</tt>, which positions EP
      against DRP, CIBA, WIMSE, receiver-attested logging, AgentROA/AIIP/CIRP,
      the Entity Attestation Token (<xref target="RFC9711"/>), OAuth Transaction
      Tokens, and Evidence Record Syntax (<xref target="RFC4998"/>). Two recent
      efforts are worth naming at the architectural level:</t>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Agent Authorization Profile for OAuth (AAP).</strong> AAP can
        express that an action requires human approval but states that the
        approval itself is out of scope and is not an offline-verifiable
        artifact. AAP and EP compose cleanly: AAP (or any policy layer) signals
        that approval is required; the EP receipt is the evidence that a named
        human gave it.</li>
        <li><strong>Decoupled authorization models</strong> (an authorization
        decision point with a standardized input contract). EP's enforcement
        point consumes such a decision; the EP receipt records the human
        authorization that the decision point required.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="invariants">
      <name>Design Invariants</name>
      <t>Every component upholds the following, and any profile claiming EP
      conformance <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve them:</t>
      <ol>
        <li><strong>Named human.</strong> The authorizing party is a real,
        accountable person (or a quorum of distinct persons), not a device,
        wallet, or vendor key.</li>
        <li><strong>Exact action.</strong> The signature covers the precise
        canonical action (tool and arguments), not a coarse scope or capability
        label.</li>
        <li><strong>Offline verifiable.</strong> A third party verifies the
        receipt without an account, without contacting the issuer, and without
        trusting the operator that produced it.</li>
        <li><strong>Fail closed.</strong> Absent a valid authorization, the
        action does not execute; absence of a receipt is the anomaly, not the
        default.</li>
        <li><strong>Non-repudiable and tamper-evident.</strong> Altering any
        covered byte invalidates verification; the record survives the issuer's
        disappearance.</li>
        <li><strong>Authorization, not wisdom.</strong> EP proves a human
        authorized the action. It does not prove the human understood it, or that
        the action was lawful, wise, or proportional. Necessary, not
        sufficient.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The dominant risk is over-trust: treating the existence of a receipt as
      proof that an action was legitimate. A receipt proves authorization
      occurred at a stated scope, currency, and authority -- nothing more.
      Deployments and downstream representations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> overstate
      it.</t>
      <t>EP proves a key signed; binding that key to the intended natural person
      is the identity-binding trust root (<xref target="c-eye"/>) and the
      explicit boundary of the architecture. Coercion of an authorized human, and
      a human authorizing an action they did not truly comprehend, are out of
      scope of the cryptographic guarantees; device-bound user verification and
      the display-fidelity requirements of the component specifications raise but
      do not eliminate these. Per-component security considerations are normative
      in each component document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4998.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9711.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nelson-agent-delegation-receipts.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.klrc-aiagent-auth.xml"/>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
