<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-human-authorization-binding-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Human-Authorization Binding">Binding Named-Human Authorization Evidence into Agent-Action Records</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-human-authorization-binding-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="3"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>human authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>binding</keyword>
    <keyword>evidence</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>A recurring pattern spans the agent-action record formats now in
      development: a record about an agent's action reserves a place for
      "the human authorization" — an approver disposition, an authority
      context, a human-override field, an actor slot, a signed grant, an
      approval reference — and leaves its semantics undefined. Each
      format, reasonably, does not want to specify human-authorization
      evidence itself; none, so far, says what filling the slot means.
      This document defines that one thing, host-agnostically: how any
      record binds named-human authorization evidence, either BY
      REFERENCE (a content digest of the authorization artifact's
      canonical bytes) or EMBEDDED (a compact, self-describing claim
      carrying named approvals and optional distinct-human quorum
      semantics), with five requirements that make the binding mean the
      same thing in every host: digest grounding, action agreement,
      verified-versus-accepted discipline, fail-closed absence, and
      embedded/referenced consistency. An informative appendix maps the
      binding onto the reserved slots of eleven current documents.
      This document defines no new authorization format: the referenced
      evidence verifies under its own specification.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Record formats for agent actions are proliferating, and almost
      all of them make the same, sound scoping decision: human
      authorization is somebody else's format. The result is a set of
      reserved-but-empty slots. A post-execution action capsule carries
      an approver disposition whose authority is opaque; a pre-execution
      permit stubs an authority context; audit-trail records carry a
      human-override field with a privacy carve-out where the human
      should be; a provenance graph has an optional actor; an audit
      architecture requires a "signed grant" whose format is an
      unassigned work item; an intent chain names an approval reference
      with no semantics. Each slot is an invitation. Eleven invitations
      with eleven ad-hoc answers would be worse than none.</t>
      <t>This document is the single answer: a host-agnostic definition
      of what it means to bind named-human authorization evidence into
      any record, plus the small set of requirements that keep the
      binding trustworthy regardless of host. It deliberately does not
      define the authorization evidence itself — a bound artifact
      verifies under its own specification (for example
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/> for
      named-human receipts and quorum) — and the appendix mappings to
      host formats are informative descriptions of public slot fields,
      offered for host authors to correct or adopt.</t>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
        all capitals, as shown here.</t>
        <t>Host record: any signed or logged record about an agent
        action that carries the binding (a capsule, permit, audit
        record, provenance node, token, or chain). Authorization
        artifact: the evidence being bound (a named-human authorization
        receipt, a quorum receipt, or an equivalent artifact defined
        elsewhere).</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="reference">
      <name>Binding by Reference</name>
      <t>The reference form is a JSON member (claim name
      "human_authorization_ref"; see <xref target="naming"/>) carried
      anywhere in the host record the host format designates:</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
"human_authorization_ref": {
  "digest": "sha256:<hex of the artifact's canonical bytes>",
  "format": "ep-receipt | ep-quorum | <other artifact type>",
  "locator": "<OPTIONAL hint URI; acquisition is out of scope>"
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The digest MUST be computed over the authorization artifact's
      canonical bytes as defined by the artifact's own specification
      (for EP artifacts, the JCS <xref target="RFC8785"/> I-JSON
      profile). The locator is a hint only: a verifier obtains the
      artifact through whatever channel the deployment provides, and
      relies on digest equality, never on the channel. The reference
      form supports disclosure minimization: a host record can travel
      without the artifact, and a relying party that requires the
      evidence fails closed until the bytes are produced.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="embedded">
      <name>The Embedded Claim</name>
      <t>The embedded form carries the evidence inline as a compact,
      self-describing claim (claim name "human_authorization"):</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
"human_authorization": {
  "v": "EP-HAC-v1",
  "action_digest": "sha256:<hex>",
  "mode": "single | quorum",
  "approvals": [
    { "approver": "<named accountable principal>",
      "role": "<OPTIONAL>",
      "key_class": "A | B | C",
      "signoff": { "...the approver's own signature object..." } }
  ],
  "policy": "<OPTIONAL policy identifier>",
  "quorum": { "required": 2, "distinct_humans": true,
              "ordered": false }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>Each approval names an accountable human principal and carries
      that principal's own signature over the action binding, verifiable
      offline under the artifact specification the claim profiles. When
      mode is "quorum", the distinct-humans and ordering semantics of
      <xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-quorum"/> apply: the required number
      of DISTINCT accountable humans, not merely distinct signatures.
      Key classes classify key custody as defined by the receipts
      specification and imply nothing about assurance levels.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="reqs">
      <name>Binding Requirements</name>
      <t>Five requirements hold for every host, and they are what make
      the binding mean the same thing everywhere:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>B1: Digest grounding. A binding is credited only against
        artifact bytes: the reference form by digest equality, the
        embedded form by verifying the contained signatures. A host
        field that merely asserts "a human approved" without either
        MUST NOT be treated as human-authorization evidence.</li>
        <li>B2: Action agreement. When the host record binds an
        action (via an action digest, a subject digest, or
        equivalent), the
        authorization artifact's action binding MUST agree with it. An
        artifact authorizing a different action MUST invalidate the
        binding, not merely weaken it.</li>
        <li>B3: Verified versus accepted. Verifying the binding
        (digests and signatures hold) is distinct from accepting it
        (the relying party trusts the artifact's issuer via
        out-of-band pinned key material). A verifier MUST report the
        two separately, and a binding from an unpinned issuer MUST NOT
        be accepted.</li>
        <li>B4: Fail-closed absence. The absence of a binding is the
        absence of evidence, never a default. A relying party whose
        policy requires human authorization MUST treat an unbound or
        unresolvable binding as insufficient. Absence becomes positive
        evidence only through a signed observed-absence statement
        naming the search performed.</li>
        <li>B5: Consistency. When a host record carries both forms,
        the embedded claim's canonical bytes MUST hash to the
        reference's digest; a mismatch invalidates both.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section anchor="naming">
      <name>Claim Naming</name>
      <t>The canonical claim names are "human_authorization_ref" and
      "human_authorization". The claim was first deployed under the
      vendor-prefixed name "ep_human_authorization"; implementations
      SHOULD accept it and MUST treat it as an alias of the embedded
      form. Host formats that already name their slot (an authority
      context, an actor, an approval reference) MAY carry the binding
      object under their own member name; the object's members, not the
      slot's name, are what this document defines.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The slot is a target. An attacker who can fill a host record's
      authorization slot chooses what a relying party later treats as
      the human's approval; every defense here exists for that reason.
      B1 removes assertion-only filling; B2 defeats splicing a genuine
      artifact from a different action (the confused-deputy case); B3
      prevents a self-issued artifact from being self-accepted; B4
      prevents silence from being read as consent; B5 prevents the two
      forms from telling two stories. Replay and one-time-use semantics
      belong to the authorization artifact and its enforcement point; a
      host record MUST NOT extend an artifact's validity by carrying
      it. The reference form additionally serves privacy: the named
      human travels only in the artifact, which can be withheld until a
      relying party with a need to know requires it — at the cost,
      by B4, of the evidence not counting until produced.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. Registration of the claim
      names in the JWT and CWT claims registries is anticipated for a
      future revision, after host-format feedback.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
          <front>
            <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-05"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-quorum" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-quorum/">
          <front>
            <title>Multi-Party Human Authorization (EP-QUORUM)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="June"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-quorum-01"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="mappings">
      <name>Host-Format Mappings (Informative)</name>
      <t>The following mappings describe, from each cited document's
      public text, where the binding fits. They are informative,
      derived from the revisions named, and offered for the host
      authors to correct or adopt; absence of a format from this list
      implies nothing, and no mapping asserts a host author's
      endorsement.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>draft-mih-scitt-agent-action-capsule-01: a capsule whose
        disposition reports a human approver carries
        human_authorization_ref alongside the disposition; B2 binds it
        to the capsule's action digest.</li>
        <li>draft-munoz-scitt-permit-profile-00: the authority_context
        member carries the reference form; the permit's decision then
        rests on evidence, not assertion.</li>
        <li>draft-sharif-agent-audit-trail-00: the human_override field
        carries the reference form, giving the named-but-privacy-carved
        human an artifact rather than an inline identity.</li>
        <li>draft-bates-atp-00: a provenance node's actor field carries
        the reference form; validators add B1-B5 to lineage checks.</li>
        <li>draft-aylward-aiga-00: the reserved X.509v3 extension slot
        carries the reference digest, binding machine identity to the
        human authorization behind its issuance.</li>
        <li>draft-nelson-agent-delegation-receipts-10: a delegation
        receipt carries the embedded claim as a co-signing layer where
        multi-party approval is required (multi-party is out of the
        host's scope by its own statement).</li>
        <li>draft-rosenberg-aiproto-cheq-00: the confirmation object's
        signature, left TBD by the host, is the embedded claim; a
        quorum of confirmations aggregates under mode "quorum".</li>
        <li>draft-yossif-psea-02: a Verifier's attestation-result
        object (out of the host's scope) carries the reference form
        binding the presence proof to the authorization it evidenced.</li>
        <li>draft-kuehlewind-audit-architecture-00: the "signed grant"
        work item (WI-5) and step-up approval responses are instances
        of the embedded claim; Authorization Transition Records carry
        the reference form.</li>
        <li>The ACP (agent communication protocols) charter's
        "confirmation and evidence requirements for AI agent
        operations": the confirmation step's evidence is the embedded
        claim; scoped access tokens carry the reference form.</li>
        <li>SPICE-adjacent intent chains: the approval_ref member is
        the reference form's digest, giving the named field its
        missing semantics.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>One adjacent family fits differently and deserves saying
      precisely. WIMSE workload credentials (WIT/WIC, and the WPT
      request binding) do not reserve a human-authorization slot;
      their working group is deliberately chartered for workload
      identity and explicitly does not define personal identities.
      They are, however, carry-capable: a WIT or transaction context
      is a JWT, and a deployment MAY carry human_authorization_ref as
      a claim alongside the workload identity — the workload
      credential then proves WHICH WORKLOAD is calling and proved
      possession, while the bound artifact proves WHICH ACCOUNTABLE
      HUMAN authorized the exact action it is about to perform. The
      two answers have different trust roots (a workload key versus a
      named human's key under organizational authority), which is why
      neither format can absorb the other and why the composition,
      rather than either alone, is what a relying party needs for an
      irreversible action.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="impl">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>The embedded claim profiles a shipped format (the EP receipt
      and quorum artifacts, three-language verifier suite with shared
      conformance vectors in one repository). The binding checks
      (digest grounding, action agreement, verified-versus-accepted,
      fail-closed absence) are exercised by the reference
      implementation's evidence-graph layer and by a deterministic
      binding vector published with the repository
      (examples/binding/human-authorization-binding-vector.mjs).</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
