<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     docName="draft-schrock-ep-presentation-binding-00"
     category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     version="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Presentation Binding">Presentation Binding for Human-Authorization Receipts: Proving the Human Approved What They Saw</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-presentation-binding-00"/>
    <author fullname="Iman Schrock">
      <organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>team@emiliaprotocol.ai</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="July" day="3"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <keyword>human authorization</keyword>
    <keyword>WYSIWYS</keyword>
    <keyword>presentation attack</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>A human-authorization receipt proves a named person produced a
      user-verified signature over a digest that commits to an exact
      action. It does not prove the surface that person signed on
      DISPLAYED that action honestly. If a signing interface shows a
      benign summary while committing a different action, the resulting
      receipt is laundered authority: cryptographically valid and
      semantically false, which is worse than no receipt at all. This is
      the presentation attack, and it is the deepest unsolved problem in
      authorization evidence, because a signature cannot attest to
      pixels. This document narrows the gap with two additive,
      offline-checkable pieces that touch no existing receipt format: a
      DETERMINISTIC RENDERER, a pure function from the canonical action
      to a byte-identical human-readable rendering, so a verifier
      RE-DERIVES the rendering from the signed bytes and rejects any
      surface that showed something else; and a DISPLAY ATTESTATION, a
      signed claim by the signing client binding the rendering it showed
      to the action it committed. Neither eliminates the presentation
      attack (nothing purely digital can), but together they convert
      "trust the vendor's UI" into "verify the rendering was the honest
      function of the signed action," and they make the residual risk
      explicit rather than hidden.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The hard part of human authorization was never the signature.
      It is the question a relying party's counsel asks first: a receipt
      of WHAT? A named human signed a digest; the digest commits to an
      action; but the human did not see the digest; they saw a screen,
      and the screen was drawn by software. If that software rendered
      "approve invoice, $1.00" while committing "wire $82,000 to account
      X", the receipt is perfect and the authority is fabricated. Every
      downstream layer — composition, sufficiency, recourse — inherits
      this weakness: they compose and grade a receipt whose meaning was
      set by an unattested rendering step.</t>
      <t>Two observations make the problem tractable without
      overclaiming. First, most presentation attacks are RENDERING
      attacks: the surface computed the display from something other
      than the signed action. That is defeatable, because a rendering
      can be made a PURE FUNCTION of the signed action and re-derived by
      any verifier. Second, the residue (a compromised or malicious
      client that renders honestly to a verifier's re-derivation while
      showing the human something else out of band) cannot be closed by
      any digital artifact and MUST be stated as residual risk, not
      papered over. This document does the first and is scrupulous about
      the second.</t>
      <section anchor="terms">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
        all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="renderer">
      <name>The Deterministic Renderer</name>
      <t>A conforming renderer is a PURE FUNCTION from a canonical
      action object to a rendering. For any two canonical actions that
      are deeply equal it MUST produce byte-identical output on every
      conformant runtime, in every locale, at any time; it MUST NOT read
      the clock, locale, environment, randomness, or any I/O. It reads a
      fixed, ordered, closed set of action fields (for example: action
      type, target, organization, initiator, policy, amount, currency,
      requested-at, risk signals), each with a fixed label, and produces
      an ordered list of label/value lines, a concatenated human-readable
      text, and a rendering digest over the canonical structure.</t>
      <t>Because the rendering is a pure function of the SIGNED action,
      a verifier re-derives it from the very bytes the receipt's action
      digest commits to and compares. A surface that displayed "$1" for
      an action that says "$82,000" cannot produce a rendering that
      re-derives; the deviation is detected offline, by anyone, without
      trusting the surface. This turns "render from the exact hashed
      bytes, never a re-described copy" from an unverifiable interface
      rule into a verifiable property.</t>
      <t>Handling untrusted content is normative: values that can carry
      display-manipulating characters (bidirectional overrides,
      control characters, homoglyph-bearing runs, or excessive length)
      MUST be neutralized by a specified, deterministic transformation
      before rendering, and a value that cannot be safely rendered MUST
      cause the renderer to refuse rather than emit a misleading line.
      The neutralization is itself part of the pure function, so the
      verifier re-derives the same neutralized rendering.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="attestation">
      <name>The Display Attestation</name>
      <t>A display attestation (wire tag EP-DISPLAY-ATTESTATION-v1) is a
      signed claim by the signing client: "I rendered THIS rendering of
      THIS action." It binds the rendering digest to the action digest
      under the client's key and is stored ALONGSIDE the receipt (in an
      audit record, a provenance bundle, or an evidence-graph node),
      never inside the signed receipt body; verifiers that predate this
      profile continue to verify receipts unchanged; verifiers that
      implement it add the display check. For high-stakes action classes
      a relying party's policy MAY require a valid display attestation
      and fail closed when it is missing or does not verify.</t>
      <t>Verified versus accepted applies here too: verifying the
      attestation (its signature holds and its rendering re-derives from
      the action) is distinct from trusting the CLIENT that made it. A
      display attestation raises the cost and auditability of a
      presentation attack; it does not, by itself, make the client
      honest.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="compose">
      <name>Composition with the Evidence Layers</name>
      <t>Presentation binding is the missing precondition under the
      rest of the stack. An authorization receipt
      (<xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts"/>) gains a
      rendering that a verifier can re-derive; a binding
      (<xref target="I-D.schrock-human-authorization-binding"/>) that
      carries such a receipt MAY additionally require the display
      attestation as part of its digest-grounding requirement; an
      evidence policy
      (<xref target="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph"/>) MAY, for a
      high-stakes reliance purpose, treat a receipt without a verifying
      display attestation as insufficient. The property this document
      adds — the human approved what a verifier can prove they were
      shown, is the one every other layer silently assumed.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="residual">
      <name>Residual Risk: WYSIWYS Is Not Solved</name>
      <t>This profile narrows the presentation-attack surface; it does
      not eliminate it, and implementers MUST NOT represent it as doing
      so. A compromised signing client can render honestly to the
      verifier's re-derivation while presenting a different artifact to
      the human through a channel the protocol cannot observe (a
      manipulated display driver, an overlaid window, a coerced
      approver). Defenses against that residue are operational and
      hardware-rooted (trusted display paths, out-of-band confirmation
      of material fields, secure enclaves) and are out of scope here.
      What this document removes is the CHEAP, SCALABLE, UNDETECTABLE
      rendering attack — the software surface that simply computed the
      display from the wrong bytes — and it makes the remaining,
      expensive residue explicit so a relying party can price it rather
      than discover it in a dispute.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The entire document is a security consideration; the residual
      risk section states the boundary. One further point: the renderer
      MUST be conservative to the point of refusing. A renderer that
      guesses at an unmodeled field, truncates silently, or best-effort
      displays hostile content trades a detectable failure for an
      undetectable one. Refusal to render is a safe outcome; a
      misleading render is the attack.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions. Registration of the render
      profile and display-attestation identifiers is anticipated for a
      future revision.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8785.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-authorization-receipts" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts/">
          <front>
            <title>Authorization Receipts for High-Risk Agent Actions</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-authorization-receipts-05"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-human-authorization-binding" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-human-authorization-binding/">
          <front>
            <title>Binding Named-Human Authorization Evidence into Agent-Action Records</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-human-authorization-binding-00"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="I-D.schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph/">
          <front>
            <title>Action Evidence Graphs and Evidence Policy Replay for High-Risk Agent Actions (EP-AEG)</title>
            <author fullname="Iman Schrock"><organization>EMILIA Protocol, Inc.</organization></author>
            <date year="2026" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schrock-ep-action-evidence-graph-00"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="impl">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>A reference implementation (the deterministic renderer, the
      display attestation, and the offline re-derivation check) is
      published Apache-2.0 in the EMILIA Protocol repository
      (lib/wysiwys/render.js) with conformance vectors and a test suite,
      including negative vectors: a rendering that does not re-derive
      from its action is rejected, and hostile display content
      (bidirectional overrides, control characters, over-length values)
      is neutralized or refused rather than rendered misleadingly.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
